<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. -->
<book>
  <chapter>
    <title>Getting started with DHIS 2</title>
    <section id="users">
      <title>Creating new users and roles</title>
      <para>This section will describe how to add new users to the DHIS 2 application.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Open User Menu</title>
        <para>To create or find a user begin with clicking on the user module displayed in the drop down menu of the Maintenance module located on the main tool bar on the top part of the displayed screen. User names already registered will appear as a list as seen in the screen shot below.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Select Users menu item</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/select_user_menu.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Search by user name</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/search_user_by_name.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>You can search for specific user names in the user list by entering the name in the filter by user name field as shown above.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="user_roles">
        <title>Define a new role</title>
        <para>As part of creating a user name you are required to define the user role. Do so by clicking on the user role appearing on the left side of the displayed screen.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Create new user role</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/select_user_role.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>This will lead you to the Role Management page where you will have to click on <guibutton>Add new</guibutton> to create a new role.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Add new user role</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/add_user_role.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>The following screen will open and here in the first text box you need to give Name of the Role such as Super User, Admin User, etc. The second text box called Description gives more information about the type of User Role that is being created for e.g. State Admin User, District Data Entry.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Role maintenance page</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/role_maintainence_page.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Next you will specify the particular data set(s) that are to be made available to the particular role. You will also need to specify the type of authority to be given to the particular user. For each of the three options namely Datasets, Reports and Authorities user can select multiple options from the scroll down menu provided against each field. A user can choose multiple options either by moving them one-by-one.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Adding a dataset to a user role</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/assign_one_dataset_user_role.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>In order for particular users to be able to enter data, you must add them to both a dataset as well as an organisational unit level. You can also select multiple datasets individually by pressing the Ctrl key on the keyboard and clicking on individual datasets.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Adding multiple datasets to user roles</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/assign_multiple_datasets_user_role.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Finally when you have entered the required fields click on <guibutton>Save</guibutton> which is located on the lower part of the displayed screen. The desired user role and related authorisation will be saved to the database, and can then be assigned to a particular user.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Add New User</title>
        <para>Under particular user role there can be more than one user. To add new users go to the User options under the Maintenance module.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Add new user</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/add_new_user.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>To add a new user, just follow these steps:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guibutton>Add New</guibutton> button.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter New User details like <guilabel>User name</guilabel>, <guilabel>Password</guilabel>, <guilabel>Confirm password</guilabel>, <guilabel>Surname</guilabel>, <guilabel>First name</guilabel> and <guilabel>Email</guilabel> in new users option tabs.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button for confirmation of new user details and follow the user error while creation of new user.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The recently created new user can be seen in main User management Screen</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can edit (like password, surname.etc) and delete the details of new/old users by selecting corresponding Users <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> Buttons.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on <guibutton>Save</guibutton> tab after editing all details of a particular selected user.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>Add or edit users</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/add_edit_users.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo>User management screen</screeninfo>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/user_management.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="mod2_4">
      <title>Logging out of DHIS2</title>
      <para>Just click on the Log out link in the top right corner to exit the application.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Logging off of DHIS 2</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/dhis2_logoff.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section id="database_design">
      <title>Quick intro to designing a DHIS 2 database</title>
      <para>The DHIS 2 application comes with a set of tools for data collection, validation, reporting and analysis, but the contents of the database, e.g. what to collect, who should collect it and on what format will depend on the context of use. This metadata need to be populated into the application before it can be used, and this can be done through the user interface and requires no programming or in-depth technical skills of the software. We call this initial process database design or customisation.</para>
      <para>This section will provide a very quick and brief introduction to DHIS 2 database design and mainly explain the various steps needed to prepare a new DHIS 2 system for use. How to do each step is explained in other chapters, and best practices on design choices will be explained in an implementers manual (expected during first half of 2011). Here are the steps to follow:</para>
      <para>1. Set up an organisational hierarchy</para>
      <para>2. Define data elements</para>
      <para>3. Define data sets and data entry forms</para>
      <para>4. Define validation rules</para>
      <para>5. Define indicators</para>
      <para>6. Define report tables and design reports</para>
      <para>7. Set up the GIS module</para>
      <para>8. Design charts and customise the dashboard</para>
      <section>
        <title>The organisational hierarchy</title>
        <para>The organisational hierarchy defines the organisation using the DHIS 2, the health facilities, administrative areas and other geographical areas used in data collection and data analysis. This dimension to the data is defined as a hierarchy with one root unit (e.g. Ministry of Health) and any number of levels and nodes below. Each node in this hierarchy is called an organisational unit in DHIS 2. The design of this hierarchy will determine the geographical units of analysis available to the users as data is collected and aggregated in this structure. There can only be one organisational hierarchy at the same time so its structure needs careful consideration. Additional hierarchies (e.g. parallel administrative boundaries to the health care sector) can be modelled using organisational groups and group sets, but the organisational hierarchy is the main vehicle for data aggregation on the geographical dimension. Typically national organisational hierarchies in public health have 4-6 levels, but any number of levels is supported. The hierarchy is built up of parent-child relations, e.g. a Country or MoH unit (the root) might have e.g. 8 parent units (provinces), and each province again ( at level 2) might have 10-15 districts as their children. Normally the health facilities will be located at the lowest level, but they can also be located at higher levels, e.g. national or provincial hospitals, so skewed organisational trees are supported (e.g. a leaf node can be positioned at level 2 while most other leaf nodes are at level 5). Typically there is a geographical hierarchy defined by the health system. e.g. where the administrative offices are located (e.g. MoH, province, district), but often there are other administrative boundaries in the country that might or might not be added, depending on how its boundaries will improve data analysis. When designing the hierarchy the number of children for any organisational unit may indicate the usefulness of the structure, e.g. having one or more 1-1 relationships between two levels is not very useful as the values will be the same for the child and the parent level. On the other extreme a very high number of children in the middle of the hierarchy (e.g. 50 districts in a province) might call for an extra level to be added in between to increase the usefulness of data analysis. The lowest level, the health facilities will often have a large number of children (10-60), but for other levels higher up in the hierarchy approx. 5-20 children is recommended. To few or too many children might indicate that a level should be removed or added. Note that it is quite easy to make changes to the upper levels of the hierarchy at a later stage, the only problem is changing organisational units that collect data (the leaf nodes), e.g. splitting or merging health facilities. Aggregation up the hierarchy is done based on the current hierarchy at any time and will always reflect the most recent changes to the organisational structure. Refer to the chapter on Organisation Units to learn how to create organisational units and to build up the hierarchy.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Data Elements</title>
        <para>The Data Element is perhaps the most important building block of a DHIS 2 database. It represents the &quot;WHAT&quot; dimension, it explains what is being collected or analysed. In some contexts this is referred to an indicator, but in DHIS 2 we call this unit of collection and analysis a <emphasis role="italic">data element</emphasis>. The data element often represents a count of something, and its name describes what is being counted, e.g. &quot;BCG doses given&quot; or &quot;Malaria cases&quot;. When data is collected, validated, analysed, reported or presented it is the data elements or expressions built upon data elements that describes the WHAT of the data. As such the data elements become important for all aspects of the system and they decide not only how data is collected, but more importantly how the data values are represented in the database, which again decides how data can be analysed and presented. </para>
        <para>It is possible to add more details to this &quot;WHAT&quot; dimension through the disaggregation dimension called data element categories. Some common categories are Age and Gender, but any category can be added by the user and linked to specific data elements. The combination of a data element&apos;s name and its assigned category defines the smallest unit of collection and analysis available in the system, and hence describes the raw data in the database. Aggregations can be done when zooming out of this dimension, but no further drill-down is possible, so designing data elements and categories define the detail of the analysis available to the system (on the WHAT dimension). Changes to data elements and categories at a later stage in the process might be complicated as these will change the meaning of the data values already captured in the database (if any). So this step is one of the more decisive and careful steps in the database design process.</para>
        <para>One best practice when designing data elements is to think of data elements as a unit of data analysis and not just as a field in the data collection form. Each data element lives on its own in the database, completely detached from the collection form, and reports and other outputs are based on data elements and expressions/formulas composed of data elements and not the data collection forms. So the data analysis needs should drive the process, and not the look an feel of the data collection forms. A simple rule of thumb is that the name of the data element must be able to stand on its own and describe the data value also outside the context of its collection form. E.g. a data element name like &quot;Total referrals&quot; makes sense when looking at it in either the &quot;RCH&quot; form or the &quot;OPD&quot; form, but on its own it does not uniquely describe the phenomena (who are being referred?), and should in stead be called &quot;Total referrals from Maternity&quot; or &quot;Total referrals from OPD&quot;. Two different data elements with different meanings, although the field on the paper form might only say &quot;Total referrals&quot; since the user of the form will always know where these referrals come from. In a database or a repository of data elements this context is no longer valid and therefore the names of the data elements become so important in describing the data. </para>
        <para>Common properties of data elements can be modelled through what is called data element groups. The groups are completely flexible in the sense that they are defined by the user, both their names and their memberships. Groups are useful both for browsing and presenting related data, but can also be used to aggregate data elements together. Groups are loosely coupled to data elements and not tied directly to the data values which means they can be modified and added at any point in time without interfering with the raw data. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Datasets and data entry forms</title>
        <para>All data entry in DHIS2 is organised through the use of Datasets. A Dataset is a collection of data elements grouped together for data collection, and in the case of distributed installs they also define chunks of data for export and import between instances of DHIS2 (e.g. from a district office local installation to a national server). Datasets are not linked directly to the data values, only through their data elements and frequencies, and as such a dataset can be modified, deleted or added at any point in time without affecting the raw data already captured in the system, but such changes will of course affect how new data will be collected. </para>
        <para>A dataset has a period type which controls the data collection frequency, which can be daily, weekly, monthly, quarterly, six-monthly, or yearly. Both which data elements to include in the dataset and the period type is defined by the user, together with a name, short name, and code.</para>
        <para>In order to use a dataset to collect data for a specific orgunit you must assign the orgunit to the dataset, and this mechanism controls which orgunits that can use which datasets, and at the same time defines the target values for data completeness (e.g. how many health facilities in a district expected to submit RCH data every month). </para>
        <para>A data element can belong to multiple datasets, but this requires careful thinking as it may lead to overlapping and inconstant data being collected if e.g. the datasets are given different frequencies and are used by the same orgunits. </para>
        <section>
          <title>Data entry forms</title>
          <para>Once you have assigned a dataset to an orgunit that dataset will be made available in Data Entry (under Services) for the orgunits you have assigned it to and for the valid periods according to the dataset&apos;s period type. A default data entry form will then be shown, which is simply a list of the data elements belonging to the dataset together with a column for inputting the values. If your dataset contains data elements with categories such as age groups or gender, then additional columns will be automatically generated in the default form based on the categories. In addition to the default list-based data entry form there are two more alternatives, the section-based form and the custom form.</para>
          <section>
            <title>Section forms</title>
            <para>Section forms allow for a bit more flexibility when it comes to using tabular forms and are quick and simple to design. Often your data entry form will need multiple tables with subheadings, and sometimes you need to disable (grey out) a few fields in the table (e.g. some categpories do not apply to all data elements), both of these functions are supported in section forms. After defining a dataset you can define it&apos;s sections with subsets of dataelements, a heading and possible grey fields i the section&apos;s table. The order of sections in a datsaset can also be defined. In Data Entry you can now start using the Section form (should appear automatically when sections are available for the selected dataset). You can switch between default and section forms in the top right corner of the data entry screen. Most tabular data entry forms should be possible to do with sections forms, and the more you can utilise the section forms (or default forms) the easier it is for you. If these two types of forms are not meeting your requirements then the third option is the completely flexible, although more time-consuming, custom data entry forms.</para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Custom Forms</title>
            <para>When the form you want to design is too complicated for the default or section forms then your last option is to use a custom form. This takes more time, but gives you full flexibility in term of the design. In DHIS 2 there is a built in HTML editor (FcK Editor) for the form designer and you can either design the form in the UI or paste in your html directly (using the Source window in the editor. In the custom form you can insert static text or data fields (linked to data elements + category) in any position on the form and you have complete freedom to design the layout of the form. Once a custom form has been added to a dataset it will be available in data entry and used automatically. You can switch back to default and section (if exists) forms in the top right corner of the data entry screen. </para>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Validation rules</title>
        <para>Once you have set up the data entry part of the system and started to collect data then there is time to define data quality checks that help to improve the quality of the data being collected. You can add as many validation rules as you like and these are composed of left and right side expressions that again are composed of data elements, with an operator between the two sides. Typical rules are comparing subtotals to totals of something. E.g. if you have two data elements &quot;HIV tests taken&quot; and &quot;HIV test result positive&quot; then you know that in the same form (for the same period and organisational unit) the total number of tests must always be equal or higher than the number of positive tests. These rules should be absolute rules meaning that they are mathematically correct and not just assumptions or &quot;most of the time correct&quot;. The rules can be run in data entry, after filling each form, or as a more batch like process on multiple forms at the same time, e.g. for all facilities for the previous reporting month. The results of the tests will list all violations and the detailed values for each side of the expression where the violation ocurred to make it easy to go back to data entry and correct the values.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Indicators</title>
        <para>Indicators represent perhaps the most powerful data analysis feature of the DHIS 2. While data elements represent the raw data (counts) being collected the indicators represent formulas providing coverage rates, incidence rates, ratios and other formula-based units of analysis. An indicator is made up of a factor (e.g. 1, 100, 100, 100 000), a numerator and a denominator, the two latter are both expressions based on one or more data elements. E.g. the indicator &quot;BCG coverage &lt;1 year&quot; is defined a formula with a factor 100, a numerator (&quot;BCG doses given to children under 1 year&quot;) and a denominator (&quot;Target population under 1 year&quot;). The indicator &quot;DPT1 to DPT3 drop out rate&quot; is a formula of 100 % x (&quot;DPT1 doses given&quot;- &quot;DPT3 doses given&quot;) / (&quot;DPT1 doses given&quot;). </para>
        <para>Most report modules in DHIS 2 support both data elements and indicators and you can also combine these in custom reports, but the important difference and strength of indicators versus raw data (data element&apos;s data values) is the ability to compare data across different geographical areas (e.g. highly populated vs rural areas) as the target population can be used in the denominator.</para>
        <para>Indicators can be added, modified and deleted at any point in time without interfering with the data values in the database. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Report tables and reports</title>
        <para>Standard reports in DHIS 2 is a very flexible way of presenting the data that has been collected. Data can be aggregated by any organisational unit or orgunit level, by data element, by indicators, as well as over time (e.g. monthly, quarterly, yearly). The report tables are custom data sources for the standard reports and can be flexibly defined in the user interface and later accessed in external report designers such as iReport or BIRT. These report designs can then be set up as easily accessible one-click reports with parameters so that the users can run the same reports e.g. every month when new data is entered, and also be relevant to users at all levels as the organisational unit can be selected at the time of running the report.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>GIS</title>
        <para>In the integrated GIS module you can easily display your data on maps, both on polygons (areas) and as points (health facilities), and either as data elements or indicators. By providing the coordinates of your organisational units to the system you can qucikly get up to speed with this module. See the GIS section for details on how to get started. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Charts and dashboard</title>
        <para>On of the easiest way to display your indicator data is through charts. An easy to use chart dialogue will guide you through the creation of various types of charts with data on indicators, organisational units and periods of your choice. These charts can easily be added to one of the four chart sections on your dashboard and there be made easily available right after log in. Make sure to set the dashboard module as the start module in user settings. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Organisation units</title>
    <para>In this section you will learn how to:</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create a new orgunit and build up the orgunit hierarchy</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create group sets and groups to add more cetegorisation to your orgunits</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to make changes to the orgunit hierarchy</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <section id="ou_hierarchy">
      <title>The organisational hierarchy</title>
      <para>The organisational hierarchy defines the organisation using the DHIS 2, the health facilities, administrative areas and other geographical areas used in data collection and data analysis. This dimension to the data is defined as a hierarchy with one root unit (e.g. Ministry of Health) and any number of levels and nodes below. Each node in this hierarchy is called an organisational unit in DHIS 2. </para>
      <para>The design of this hierarchy will determine the geographical units of analysis available to the users as data is collected and aggregated in this structure. There can only be one organisational hierarchy at the same time so its structure needs careful consideration. </para>
      <para>Additional hierarchies (e.g. parallel administrative boundaries to the health care sector) can be modeled using organisational groups and group sets, but the organisational hierarchy is the main vehicle for data aggregation on the geographical dimension. Typically national organisational hierarchies in public health have 4-6 levels, but any number of levels is supported. </para>
      <para>The hierarchy is built up of parent-child relations, e.g. a Country or MoH unit (the root) might have e.g. 8 child units (provinces), and each province again ( at level 2) might have 10-15 districts as their children. Normally the health facilities will be located at the lowest level, but they can also be located at higher levels, e.g. national or provincial hospitals, so skewed organisational trees are supported (e.g. a leaf node can be positioned at level 2 while most other leaf nodes are at level 5). </para>
      <para>Note that it is quite easy to make changes to the upper levels of the hierarchy at a later stage, the only problem is changing organisational units that collect data (the leaf nodes), e.g. splitting or merging health facilities. Aggregation up the hierarchy is done based on the current hierarchy at any time and will always reflect the most recent changes to the organisational structure. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Organisation unit maintenance</title>
      <section id="orgunit">
        <title>Organisation units</title>
        <para>This is where you can create organisation units (from now on referred to as orgunits) and build up the orgunit hierarchy. Orgunits are added one by one as either root unit or a child of a selected unit. The left side menu represents the current organisational hierarchy and if you select a unit there you will see its children listed in the main list of orgunits in the middle of the screen. When an orgunit is selected in the left side menu you can also add new child units to it. To locate an orgunit in the hierarchy you can either navigate through the tree by expanding the branches (click on the + symbol), or search for it by opening the search field (click the green symbol above the root of the hierarchy). In search you can either search for the orgunit name or its code, both will only show exact matches (case-insensitive). To add a new orgunit first select its parent and then click on the Add new button in the top right corner of the list of orgunits. To add a new root orgunit make sure no orgunit is selected in the menu and click on &quot;Add new&quot;. The details of adding a new orgunit are explained in the Editing organisational units section below.</para>
        <section id="ou_edit">
          <title>Editing organisation units</title>
          <para>To edit the properties of an existing orgunit first select its parent (if any) in the left side menu, then locate the orgunit in the listed orgunits, and finally click on the &quot;Edit&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/edit.png" align="center"/> button next to the name of the orgunit that you want to modify. The following properties can be defined in the Edit (or Create new) window:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Name: Define the precise name of the orgunit in this field. Each orgunit must have a unique name. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Short name: Typically, an abbreviation of the full name. This attribute is often used in reports to display the name of the orgunit, where there is limited space available. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Code: In many countries, orgunits are assigned a code. This code can be entered in this field. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Opening date: Used to control which orgunits that where existing at a point in time, e.g. when analysing historical data. Default is 1994-01-01 and can be used when the orgunit was already existing when the data collection process started. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Registers data: This property is used to identify which orgunits that can register data or not. Sometimes administrative orgunits at higher levels in the hierarchy are not supposed to register any data. This can help control the data entry process as only orgunits with this property set to Yes will be availabel for data entry. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Comment: Any additional information that you would like to add can be put here. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Coordinates: This field is used to create the maps in the GIS module. Paste in the coordinates of the orgunit in this field, either a polygon (for orgunits that represent an administrative boundary) or a point (for health facilities). Without this information the GIS module will not work. It might be more efficient to import these coordinates later as a batch job for all orgunits using the import module. See the GIS chapter for more details.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>URL: You can use this field to insert a URL link to an external web site that has additional information about this specific orgunit.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="ou_groupsets">
        <title>Organisation unit group sets</title>
        <para>Group sets can be understood as a flexible tool to add more categorisation to orgunits. Any number of group sets can be added, but as a default start all databases will have the two group sets &quot;Type&quot; and &quot;Ownership&quot;. Using these group sets will simplify how reporting is done. </para>
        <para>While a group set like &quot;Type&quot; describes a measure dimension, the actual categories are represented by the groups, and the categorisation of an orgunit through the orgunit&apos;s group memberships. This can be understood as a parallel hierarchy of orgunits with the group set as the root (&quot;Type&quot;), the groups at level 2 (e..g &quot;Clinic&quot;, &quot;Hospital&quot;, &quot;Dispensary&quot;), and the actual orgunits at level 3. The group set can as such provide additional information and dimensionality to the data analysis as data is easily filtered, organised, or aggregated by groups within a group set. </para>
        <para>For this aggregation to work without any duplication in the data some rules are necessary. A group set is always exclusive, which means that an orgunit cannot be member of more than one group in a group set. If you try otherwise you will get notified by the application and the action not allowed. Furthermore it is possible to define whether a group set is compulsory or not, which will affect the completeness of the data when analysing data using group sets. Compulsory means that ALL orgunits must be member of a group in that group set. </para>
        <para>We recommend that you approach the orgunit grouping in the following sequence (and one group set at a time):</para>
        <para>1. Add a new group set (or use one of the ones)</para>
        <para>2. Add new groups (names only) and then when you are done go back to the group set and add the groups you just created (in edit group set mode).</para>
        <para>3. Go back to each group, one by one, go to edit mode and assign the orgunits that should be member of the group.</para>
        <para>If you start with 3) above then you will easily end up with exclusive violations when later adding groups to a group set. Following the sequence above this will be checked at the time of assigning orgunits to a group (since the system know which group set that group belongs to).</para>
        <para>To add a new group set click on the &quot;Add new&quot; button.</para>
        <section id="ou_groupsets_edit">
          <title>Editing organisation unit group sets</title>
          <para>Click on the &quot;Edit&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/edit.png" align="center"/> button next to the name of the orgunit group set that you want to modify. The following properties can be defined in the Edit (or Create new) window:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Name: Provide a precise name for the group set.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Description: Describe the phenomena the group set is measuring/capturing.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Compulsory: Indicate whether ALL orgunits need to be member of a group in this group set or not.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para> groups/Selected groups: Here you assign groups to your group set by using the arrow buttons to move highlighted groups between the two lists (/selected). If no groups appear in the list then you must go to orgunit groups and create new groups there first. Note that assigning groups that will violate the exclusive rule on group sets is not possible, e.g. adding a group that already has assigned an orgunit that again is already member of a group that has already been selected by this group set, will not be possible since one orgunit will end up with two group memberships in the same group set. To avoid such situations we recommend first adding groups to group sets, and then orgunits to groups.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="ou_groups">
        <title>Organisation unit groups</title>
        <para>Here you can add new and manage existing organisation groups and their memberships. To add a new orgunit group click on the &quot;Add new&quot; button in the top right corner of the list of groups. </para>
        <section id="ou_groups_edit">
          <title>Editing organisation unit groups</title>
          <para>Click on the &quot;Edit&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/edit.png" align="center"/> button next to the name of the orgunit group that you want to modify. The following properties can be defined in the Edit (or Create new) window:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Name: Provide a precise name for the orgunit group.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Organisation unit tree selection: This is where you assign orgunits to the group. The tree supports multiple selection so select all the orgunits that you want to add (the selected ones appear with orange color) and click on &quot;Save&quot;. Click on &quot;Cancel&quot; to undo your changes and return to the list of orgunit groups. Use the &quot;Select at level&quot; button and dropdown if you want to select all orgunits at a specific level in the hierarchy (e.g. all districts). </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="ou_level">
        <title>Organisation unit level</title>
        <para>Here you specify a contextual name for each level in the hierarchy, e.g. &quot;Country&quot;, &quot;Province&quot;, &quot;District&quot;, &quot;Health Facility&quot;, and these names will be used all over the application where levels are referred to. This page will take some time to load if the orgunit hierarchy is very big.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="hierarchy_operations">
        <title>Hierarchy operations</title>
        <para>Here you can move orgunits around in the hierarchy by changing the parent of a selected orgunit. This process is done in three steps:</para>
        <para>1. Select the orgunit you want to move (in the hierarchy in the left side menu) and click &quot;Confirm&quot; under the &quot;Select an organisation unit to move&quot; label.</para>
        <para>2. Select the new parent orgunit (again by using the hierarchy in the left side menu). If no parent is selected then the orgunit will be moved up to root level (top of the hierarchy). Click on the &quot;Confirm&quot; button under the &quot;Select the new parent organisation unit for the one to move&quot; label.</para>
        <para>3. Click on the &quot;Move&quot; button to apply your changes to the hierarchy.</para>
        <para>Your changes will be immediately reflected in the left side menu hierarchy. At any time in the process (before hitting the Move button) you can click on the &quot;Reset&quot; button to unselect orgunit to move and the new parent.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
 
  <chapter>
  <title>Data elements</title>
  <para>When the ‘Data Elements and Indicators’ options is chosen from the main Maintenance menu, the following screen appears:</para>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_main.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
  <para>From the left side menu or by clicking on the sections listed in the central area you can access the various sections on data elements;</para>
  <para>Data Element, Data Element Group, Data Element Group Editor, Data Element Group Set, Data Element Category, Data Element Category Combination. </para>
  <section>
    <title>Data element maintenance</title>
    <para>Each of the options for maintenance of  data elements will be described in the following section.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data elements. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element group</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data element groups. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element group editor</para>
        <para>Easily add or remove data elements to and from data element groups. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element group set editor</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data elements group sets.   </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data element categories</para>
        <para>Create, modify, view and delete data element categories. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section id="dataElement">
      <title>Data elements</title>
      <para>Data elements form the basis of DHIS2. Data elements define what is actually recorded in system, e.g. number of immunisations or number of cases of malaria. The actual creation and definition of the data elements themselves are far beyond the scope of this manual to describe, but it is assumed that an administrator will be provided with a list of standardised data elements for inclusion into the DHIS2 system. </para>
      <para>To access the data element maintenance module, choose Maintenance-&gt;Data elements-&gt;Data element. </para>
      <para>The ‘Filter by name’ will allow you to filter a range of data elements if you know either the full name of the data element, or just a part of it. Type the name
               into the search field and any matching data elements are displayed below.
               You can also choose ‘Filter by group/view all’ to narrow down a data
               element search within a particular data element group. In default mode, this
               field will display all the data elements in the application.
               The ‘Get PDF’ button can be clicked to generate a .pdf file of all the data
               elements. The &apos;Sort&apos; button can be used to sort the data elements into alphabetical order. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_main2.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>To add a new data element, click the &apos;Add new&apos; button. There are various options available from this page that allow the user to modify data elements already present in the database. Each of the options are described below in the &quot;Editing data elements&quot;. </para>
      <section>
        <title>Editing data elements</title>
        <para>Click the &quot;Edit&quot;<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/edit.png" align="center"/> button to modify the properties of a data element that has been previously defined. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_edit.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Name: Define the precise name of the data element in this field. Each data element must have a unique name. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Short name: Typically, an abbreviation of the full data element name. This attribute is often used in reports to display the name of the data element, where there is limited space available. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Alternative name: Allows the definition of an alternative name of the data element. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Code: In many countries, data elements are assigned a code. This code can be entered in this field. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Description: Allows a full textual description of the data element to be entered. The user should be as precise as possible, and include full information on how the data element is measured and what its meaning is. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Active: Defines whether a given data element is active or not. Data elements marked as inactive, will not be displayed in the data entry screens. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Domain type: Defines whether a data element is an aggregate or patient type of data element. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Value type: Defines the type of data this data element will be used to record. Currently there are four options: number, text, yes/no (boolean), and date. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Aggregation operator: Defines the default aggregation operation that will be used on this data element. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>URL: A URL having an in-depth description of the data element can be entered in the ‘URL’ field. This could be for instance, a link to a metadata repository or registry that contains detailed technical information about the definition and measurement of the data element. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Combination of categories: Defines which category combination the data element should have. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data element group sets: Click the check box to activate this option  hen choose which data element group sets this data element should belong to. Available data element group sets are displayed din the upper window. Click the desired data element group set, then the <guibutton>&quot;Add selected&quot;</guibutton> button to add the data element to the group set. To remove a data element from a group set, click the data element group set in the lower list, and then click<guibutton> &quot;Remove selected&quot;</guibutton>. </para>
            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_elements_group_sets.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Calculated: This option is available only when a data element is created. </para>
            <para>Select the data elements that will be used to define the calculated data element, and then click &quot;Add selected&quot; to add them calculated data element composition list. Fill in the correct factor for the data element calculation component (defaults to 1). Component elements of the calculated data element can be removed from the definition by pressing the &quot;Remove&quot; button. <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_calculated_define.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Aggregation levels:  The Aggregation Levels option allows the data element to be aggregated at one or more levels. When the user clicks on the Aggregation levels option, a drop down menu appears which displays available aggregation levels. The desired aggregation level is then selected by clicking the ‘Add Selected’ button. By default, the aggregation will start at the lowest assigned organisation unit. If e.g. Chiefdom is selected below it means that Chiefdom, District, and National aggregates will use Chiefdom (the  highest aggregation level available) as the data source, and PHU data will not be included. PHU data will still be available for the PHU level, but not included in aggregations to the levels above. If District and Chiefdom are both selected then the District and National level aggregates will use District data as their source, Chiefdom will use Chiefdom, and PHU will use PHU. Read more about aggregation levels in the Reporting chapter i the section on data sources for reporting. <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_aggregation_levels.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>After making the required changes, click ‘Save’ to institute them. The ‘Cancel’ button aborts all changes made.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Data element translation</title>
        <para>DHIS2 provides functionality to translate existing data elements into other languages. Simply press the translate button <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/i18n.png" align="center"/> to get stared. The following dialogue will appear. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_translate.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>The reference language is displayed in the upper right portion of the dialogue. Choose a locale to translate the data element into by selecting an option from the locale drop-down menu. Specify the name, short-name and description in the target language. Press &quot;Save&quot; to save your changes. </para>
        <para>The &quot;Details&quot; section of this dialogue will allow you add a new locale if it is not already present in the database. There are two options:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Language code</para>
            <para>Refers to the ISO 639-1 (two-letter code) language code. Refer to this <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_ISO_639-1_codes">web page</ulink> for a detailed listing of language codes. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Country code</para>
            <para>Refers to the ISO 3166-1-alpha-2 code. A complete listing is available <ulink url="http://www.iso.org/iso/country_codes/iso_3166_code_lists/english_country_names_and_code_elements.htm">here</ulink>. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The combination of these two codes together, forms a &quot;locale&quot; code, which is composed of the combination of the location and language. A very comprehensive discussion of the technical standard (RFC 3066) is available <ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3066.txt">here</ulink>.  This <ulink url="http://www.i18nguy.com/unicode/language-identifiers.html">page</ulink> provides a very comprehensive list of recognised locale codes. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Deleting a data element</title>
        <para>Simply press the delete button <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/delete.png" align="center"/> to delete a data element. Note that this operation is only possible if there is no data attached to the data element itself.  The user will be prompted to ensure that the data element should be deleted. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_delete.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Displaying data element details</title>
        <para>This operation displays an in-line panel in the browser which displays all metadata about a given data element. Press the information button <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/information.png" align="center"/>to access this view. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="dataElementGroup">
      <title>Data element groups</title>
      <para>Data element groups provide a mechanism for classifying related data elements into a common theme. For instance, two data elements &quot;Measles immunisation&quot; and  &quot;BCG Immunisation&quot; might be grouped together into a data element group &quot;Childhood immunisation&quot;. To access the data element group maintenance page, click Maintenance-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Data Element Group . The following screen will be displayed. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_groups_main.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Similar to the &quot;Data element&quot; maintenance page, data elements groups can be searched with by entering a search string in the &quot;Filter by name&quot; field. </para>
      <para>To add a new data element group, click the <guibutton>&quot;Add new&quot;</guibutton> button. <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_group_add.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>
      <para>Fill in the &quot;Name&quot; field and then select all data elements that should belong to the group from the left panel. Click the &quot;Move selected&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_right.png" align="center"/>button to add the selected data elements to the data element group. Click the &quot;Remove selected&quot; button to remove all data elements from the group that have been selected in the right panel.  Finally, click the &quot;Add&quot; button to save changes, or the &quot;Cancel&quot; button to discard any changes. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="dataElementGroupEditor">
      <title>Data element group editor</title>
      <para>The data element group  editor provides advanced functionality to the administrator to allow multiple data elements to be added or removed from a group. It is also possible to create new data element groups, rename existing groups, and delete groups entirely. To access the data element group editor, press <guimenu>&quot;Maintainers-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Data element group editor&quot;</guimenu> from the main DHIS2 menu. The following screen will appear. <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_group_editor_start.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>
      <para>Data element groups area listed alphabetically in the leftmost panel. By clicking on a data element group, the current members of that group (data elements) are listed in the centre panel. Available data elements that can be added to the data element group appear are listed alphabetically in the rightmost panel. To remove an existing data element from the group, click the name of the data element in the centre panel, and then press the &quot;Move right&quot;  <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_right.png" align="center"/> button. To add data elements to the group, select them from the leftmost panel, and click the &quot;Move left&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_left.png" align="center"/> button. Press the <guibutton>&quot;Update data element group member&quot;</guibutton> button to save your changes. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_group_editor_select.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section id="dataElementGroupSet">
      <title>Data element group sets</title>
      <para>Data element group sets allow multiple data element groups to be categorised into a set. Data element group sets are used during analysis and reporting to combine similar data element groups into a common theme. To access the data element group set maintenance module, choose &quot;Maintenance-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Data element group set&quot;.  Similar to the other data element maintenance modules, new data element group sets can be added by pressing the &quot;Add new button&quot;.  Other operations include Edit, Translate, Delete and Information, similar to the other modules in this section. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_group_set_start.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Existing data element group  set members can be edited by clicking the &quot;Edit&quot; button <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/edit.png" align="center"/> of the desired data element group set as seen below.</para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_group_set.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>Available data element groups are displayed in the left panel. They can be moved into the selected data element group set by pressing the &quot;Move right&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_right.png" align="center"/> button. Data element groups that are currently members of the data element group set are displayed in the right hand panel. They can be removed from the data element group set by clicking the desired data element group and pressing the &quot;Move left&quot;<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_left.png" align="center"/> button.  The ordering of the data element groups can be set with the &quot;Move Up&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_up.png" align="center"/> and &quot;Move Down&quot; <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_down.png" align="center"/>arrows. This ordering will be used in the datamart and reports to order the data element groups.  Press the <guibutton>&quot;Update&quot;</guibutton> button to save any changes and the <guibutton>&quot;Cancel&quot;</guibutton> button to discard all changes. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="dataElementCategory">
      <title>Data element categories</title>
      <para>Data element categories can be used to disaggregate data elements into individual atomic components. Data element categories are typically a concept, such as Gender, Age or  Disease Status. Data elements such as &quot;Number of cases of confirmed malaria&quot; are often broken into smaller component parts to determine, for instance, the number of confirmed malaria cases of particular age groups. As an example, three data element categories: Under 1, 1-5 and Over 5 could be created. They could be assigned as categories to the data element, which would then create in the data entry screens, three separate fields for this data element namely: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Number of confirmed malaria cases (Under 1)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Number of confirmed malaria cases (1-5)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Number of confirmed malaria cases (Over 5)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Effective use of data element categories greatly simplifies the process of setting up the DHIS2 system, as the data element categories can be reused to disaggregate many different data elements. Otherwise, each of the data elements listed above, would need to be created separately. Judicious use of data element categories will greatly simplify the DHIS2 implementation, and allow for subsequent advanced analysis. </para>
      <para>Data element categories are composed of category options. Category options must be defined when a data element category is created for the first time. Subsequent changes to the data element category, i.e.  adding or deleting new category options, are not allowed once the data element category has been created. </para>
      <caution>
        <para>It is critical that the proper categories and category options are defined in the initial definition step, as further changes to the category and its options will are not possible. </para>
      </caution>
      <para>To access the data element category maintenance module, press &quot;Maintenance-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Data element category&quot;. The following screen will be displayed. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_categories_start.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Similar to the other data element maintains modules, data element categories can be filtered by typing the name of the data element category (or a portion of it) into the &quot;Filter by name&quot; field. To add a new data element category, press the &quot;Add new&quot; button which will then display the following screen. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_categories_add_new.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Type the name of the new data element category in the &quot;Name&quot; field in the &quot;Details&quot; region. Category options can be added by typing the name of the category option in the &quot;Category option&quot; region and pressing the <guibutton>&quot;Add category option&quot;</guibutton> button. Category options can be reordered using the &quot;Move Up&quot;<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_up.png" align="center"/> and &quot;Move Down&quot;<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/move_down.png" align="center"/> buttons. Categories options can be deleted by selecting the data element category option and pressing the &quot;Delete&quot;<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/delete.png" align="center"/> button. Once all data element categories options have been added to the data element category, press the <guibutton>&quot;Add&quot;</guibutton> button to save all changes or the <guibutton>&quot;Cancel&quot;</guibutton>  button to discard any changes.<caution>
          <para>All data element category options must be added and defined properly in this step. Subsequent alterations to the data element category (other than reordering of the category options themselves) is not possible. </para>
        </caution></para>
    </section>
    <section id="dataElementCategoryCombo">
      <title>Data element category combinations</title>
      <para>Data element category combinations allow multiple data element categories to be combined into a related set. As an example, a data element &quot;Number of new HIV infections&quot; might be disaggregated according to the following categories. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Age: &quot;Under 5&quot;, &quot;5-15&quot;, &quot;15-24&quot;, &quot;24 and above&quot;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Gender: Male, Female</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para> In this example, there would be two levels of disaggregation, consisting of two separate data element categories, each consisting of several data element category options. In most HMIS systems, different data elements are disaggregated according to a common set of categories. By combining these different categories into a data element category combination and assigning these combinations to data elements, the appropriate disaggregation levels can be applied efficiently and quickly to a large number of data elements. </para>
      <para>To access the data element category combination maintenance module, select &quot;Maintenance-&gt;Data element and indicators-&gt;Data element category combinations&quot; from the main DHIS2 menu. As with the  other maintains modules, you can filter the listed category combinations by entering the name (or portion thereof) of the category combination. Other operations such as &quot;Edit&quot;, &quot;Delete&quot; and &quot;Information&quot; should be familiar to the reader. </para>
      <para>To add a new category combination, click the &quot;Add new&quot; button. The following dialogue will be displayed. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_category_combo_add_new.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Type the name of the category combination in the &quot;Name&quot; field, and then select the desired categories from the left panel. Press the &quot;Move right&quot; button to add the selected categories to the category combination. Press &quot;Move left&quot; to remove any categories that should not be part of the category combination. </para>
      <caution>
        <para>Categories can only be added to a category combination at this step. Categories can be removed from category combinations later by editing the category combination, however, it is not allowed to add additional categories once the combination has been created. Ensure that the category combination and its respective categories is final before you create the category combination and assign it to a data element. </para>
      </caution>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
  
  <chapter>
    <title>Datasets and data entry forms</title>
    <section id="datasets">
      <title>Data Entry Forms and Datasets in DHIS2</title>
      <para>All data entry in DHIS2 is organised through the use of Datasets. You can add and edit datasets in Maintenance-&gt;Datasets. A DataSet is a collection of data elements grouped together for data collection and data export between instances of DHIS2 (e.g. from a district office local installation to a national server). </para>
      <para>A dataset also has a frequency which controls the data collection frequency, which can be daily, weekly, monthly, quarterly, six-monthly, or yearly. Both which data elements to include in the dataset and the frequency is set in the Add/Edit Dataset window, together with a name, short name, and code. In order to use a dataset to collect data for a specific orgunit you must assign the orgunit to the dataset, and this mechanism controls which orgunits that can use which datasets. </para>
      <para>You can assign orgunits to a dataset in the Dataset Management (list of available datasets are shown) by clicking on the blue folder icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the dataset you would like to modify. Alternatively you can manage orgunit assignments for all datasets together in the Dataset Assignment Editor (available in the right-side menu for Datasets). </para>
      <para>Your dataset will then be ready to be used in Services-&gt;Data Entry for the orgunits that you have assigned and for periods according to your selected frequency (period type).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Data Entry Forms</title>
      <para>Once you have assigned a dataset to an orgunit that dataset will be made available in Data Entry (under Services) for the orgunits you have assigned it to. A default data entry form will then be shown, which is simply a list of the data elements you belonging to the dataset together with a column for inputting the values. If your dataset contains data elements with a non-default categorycombination, such as age groups or gender then additional columns will be automatically generated in the default form based on the different options/dimensions. </para>
      <para>If you use more than one categorycombination you will get multiple columns in the data entry form with different column headings for the options. In addition to the default list-based data entry form there are two more alternatives, the section-based form and the custom form.</para>
      <section id="dataset_sections">
        <title>Section forms</title>
        <para>Section forms allow for a bit more flexibility when it comes to using tabular forms and are quick and simple to design. Often your data entry form will need multiple tables with subheadings, and sometimes you need to disable (grey out) a few fields in the table, both of these functions are supported in section forms. </para>
        <para>When designing a section form the procedure is as follows: </para>
        <para>1) Set up your dataset as described above </para>
        <para>2) Open the DataSet Section window (from right side menu under Datasets) and add your sections one by one </para>
        <para>3) For each section you have the option to disable certain fields by accessing the Section grey field management window under Operations (second icon). </para>
        <para>4) Finally, in Dataset Section management, select your Dataset, then leave [All] in Category Combo, and click on Sort section to sort the order of appearance of your sections in the data entry form. </para>
        <para>5) In Data Entry you can now start using the Section form (should appear automatically when sections are available for the selected dataset). You can switch between default and section forms in the top right corner of the data entry screen.</para>
        <section id="dataset_sections_edit">
          <title>Adding/editing dataset sections</title>
          <para>Under Maintenance-&gt;Dataset select Dataset Section in the right-side menu. To add new section first select your Dataset (above the section list) and then the Category Combo, and click on the &lt;Add new&gt; button. </para>
          <para>NOTE that you can only use one categorycombo per section (this is because each categorycombo requires a new table). </para>
          <para>To Edit an existing Section simply click on the Edit icon under Operations next to the section you want to edit. </para>
          <para>In the Add/Edit Dataset Section window you must provide a Name and a Title for your section. The Title is used as a heading above the section&apos;s table in the data entry form. The Name is used in Dataset section management when listing available sections. </para>
          <para>Under Available data elements you will see all the data elements allocated to your dataset that have not yet been assigned to a section. You can change the order of appearance of the selected data elements by using the green arrows. This is then the order used in the data entry form. </para>
          <para>Fill in the Name, Title, select the data elements to use, and then Save the section.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="grey_field">
          <title>Grey field management</title>
          <para>In Dataset section management, locate the section you want to modify and click on the Section grey field management icon under Operations. You will then see the table corresponding to your section and for each field there is a &lt;Disable&gt; button. </para>
          <para>For the fields you want to disable you simply click on the &lt;Disable&gt; button and you will see that the field goes grey and that the button changes to &lt;Enable&gt;. To undo the disabling you then click on Enable. When you have finished the disabling then click on &lt;Done&gt;.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="custom_forms">
        <title>Custom Forms</title>
        <para>When the form you want to design is to complicated for the default or section forms then your last option is to use a custom form. This takes more time, but gives you full flexibility in term of the design. We use a built in HTML editor (FcK Editor) for the form designer and you can either design the form in the UI or paste in your html directly (using the Source window in the editor. </para>
        <para>Once a custom form has been added to a dataset it will be available in data entry and used automatically. You can switch back to default and section (if exists) forms in the top right corner of the data entry screen.</para>
        <para>To add a custom form design to a dataset then first locate your dataset in the Dataset Management window and click on the Design data entry form icon under Operations (the fifth icon), see the mouse-over text to be sure. </para>
        <para>First provide a Name for the form. There are a few important buttons in the Editor that you must pay special attention to. The blue monitor icon is the full screen mode on/off button, which can be very useful. The there is a Source button that shows the html code for your form. </para>
        <para>If you already have the html for your form then you should start by pasting it in here. Click on Source again to go back to preview/non-html mode. Then there is an icon in the top right corner with a + sign on it, this will open a list of available data elements to add to your form, the Data Element Selector window. </para>
        <para>All the input fields need to have a link to a data element in order to save the value to the correct data element. To add a data element click on the data element, then on the desired categoryoptioncombo, and then click on OK. This will add a data field to your form which shows the linked data element+catoptioncombo. </para>
        <para>You can to intermediary saving by clicking on the Save button, and this will not close the window. We recommend saving often not to loose your work. </para>
        <para>When you are done or want to test your form in data entry click on &lt;Save and close&gt;. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Data entry</title>
    <section>
      <title>Learning Objectives</title>
      <para>After reading this chapter you will be able to understand:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to do data entry</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to do data validation</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to use standard and customised data entry screens</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="dataEntry">
      <title>Data entry</title>
      <para>The data entry module is where data is manually registered in the DHIS 2 database.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Opening the Data Entry screen</title>
        <para>Entering data in DHIS 2 is a very simple task, and involves the following steps. Click on the services tab displayed on the main menu. A drop down menu will appear listing the services provided by DHIS2. Click on the <guibutton>Data Entry</guibutton> option.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Open DHIS2 data entry screen</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/open_data_entry_screen.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>You will now enter the data entry module. This module is where the services/ data values are captured / registered into the system. The screen display will be like the screen-shot shown below.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Main data entry screen</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/data_entry_screen_main.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Navigate organisation tree and select organisation unit</title>
        <para>In order to enter data you will first have to select the particular organisation unit (e.g. Sub Centre/PHC/districts etc) for which you are going to enter data. Simply clicking on the concerned organisation unit from the organisation units hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Select Organisational unit</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/data_entry_screen_select_org_unit.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Entering data</title>
        <para>When you select an organisational unit (or orgunit) from the organisation unit tree, datasets available for this orgunit will then appear as a drop-down list in the data set box as depicted below.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Select dataset</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/data_entry_select_data_set.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>If the dataset field is disabled it means that there are no datasets assigned for the selected organisation unit or that your user role is not authorised to enter data. For now we shall limit our concern to data entry. You will learn to create and assign datasets to specific organisation unit in a later module. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Data Quality</title>
    <para>The data quality module provides means to improve the quality of the data in the system. This can be done through validation rules and various statistical checks.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Learning Objectives</title>
      <para>After reading this module you will be able to understand:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>What is data quality and its importance for HMIS.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to do data quality check at point of data entry.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to create data validation rules.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to carry out data triangulation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to analyze data status.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Overview of data quality check</title>
      <para>Ensuring data quality is a key concern in building an effective HMIS. Data quality has different dimensions including:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Correctness:</emphasis> Data should be within the normal range for data collected at that facility. There should be no gross discrepancies when compared with data from related data elements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Completeness:</emphasis> Data for all data elements for all health facilities/blocks/Taluka/districts should have been submitted.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Consistency:</emphasis> Data should be consistent with data entered during earlier months and years while allowing for changes with reorganization, increased work load, etc. and consistent with other similar facilities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Timeliness:</emphasis> All data from all health facilities/blocks/Taluka/districts should be submitted at the appointed time.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Data quality checks</title>
      <para>Data quality checking can be done through various means, including:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>At point of data entry, the software can check the data entered to see if it falls within the min-max ranges of that data element over the last six months or as defined by the user.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Defining various validation rules, which can be run once the user has finished data entry. The user can also check the entered data for a particular period and Organization Unit(s) against the validation rules, and display the violations for these validation rules. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Analysis of data sets, ie. examining gaps in data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data triangulation which is comparing the same data or indicator from different sources.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Data quality check at the point of data entry </title>
      <para>Data quality can be checked at the point of data entry through setting the minimum and maximum value range for each element manually or generating the min-max values using the DHIS 2 if there is historical data available for that data element. </para>
      <section>
        <title>Setting the minimum and maximum value range manually </title>
        <para>If you are using the default entry screen click on the element for which you want to set the min-max value. A pop-up window will appear in which you can enter the vaules. On subsequent data entry if the value entered does not fall within the set min-max range the text box will change colour to red. The user will also get a pop-up as shown below. This change in colour is a prompt to check the data entered and make necessary correction. On the data entry screen the users also have the option to add a comment on how the discrepant figure might be explained (if required). This you can do by using the drop down menu of the comment box. In case you are using the custom data entry screen which is displayed when you deselect the default data entry form option on the top right corner of the screen. In this case the minimum and maximum values can be added by double-clicking on the data entry box instead of the data element.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Generated min-max values </title>
        <para>It is possible to generate the min-max value, element-wise, using the DHIS2. In such case you merely need to click on the Generate min-max button near the upper right corner. In case of default data entry screen the min and max values, when generated, will appear on the left and right side of the data entry box. In case you deselect the default data entry form the generated values will appear on the top right end of the screen.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="validationRule">
      <title>Validation Rule</title>
      <para>This module provides management of validation rules. A validation rule is based on an expression which defines a relationship between a number of data elements. The expression has a left side and a right side and an operator which defines whether the former must be less than, equal to or greater than the latter. The expression forms a condition which should assert that certain logical criterias are met. For instance, a validation rule could assert that the total number of vaccines given to infants is less than or equal to the total number of infants.</para>
      <para>To add a validation rule, click the add new button. First, provide a descriptive <emphasis role="italic">name</emphasis> for the validation rule. The name must be unique among the validation rules. Second, provide a description for the validation rule. Third, select an operator. The operator options are <emphasis role="italic">equal</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">not equal</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">greater than</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">greater than or equal</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">less than</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">less than or equal to</emphasis>. Then define the left side and right side of the validation rule expression. First, provde a description for the expression. Second, build the expression with the expression builder. The expression is mathematical and contain data elements as well as integers and mathematical operators. Data elements can be included by double-clicking one in the available data elements list to the righ. Alternatively one can select a data element and click the insert button. Mathematical operators can be included by clicking the corresponding button under the expression builder area. Save the expression by clicking <emphasis role="italic">save</emphasis>, then save the validation rule by clicking <emphasis role="italic">save</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>To edit a validation rule, click the <emphasis role="italic">edit</emphasis>icon next to the relevant validation rule in the list. Then follow the same producedures as above.</para>
      <para>To delete a validation rule, click the <emphasis role="italic">delete</emphasis>icon next to the relevant validation rule in the list.</para>
      <para>To view validation rule details, click the <emphasis role="italic">view details</emphasis>icon next to the relevant validation rule in the list.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="validationRuleGroup">
      <title>Validation Rule Group</title>
      <para>A validation rule group provides a mechanism for classifying related data elements. Another advantate of using validation rule grops is that it can later be run separately, contrary to running all validation rules.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="validationRuleAnalysis">
      <title>Validation Rule Analysis</title>
      <para>The validation rule analysis function will test validation rules against the data in the system. Validation violations will be reported in cases where the condition defined through the validation rule expression is not met, ie. the condition is false. </para>
      <para>First, enter a start date and an end date for which data should be included in the analysis. The date picker widget may be used to select dates. Second, choose between including all validation rules or a single group. Third, choose between including the selected organisation unit only or the selected organisation unit with all children in the analysis. Fourth, select the organisation unit. Finally, click <emphasis role="italic">validate</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>The analysis process while run for a while dependending on the amount of data that is being anaylysed. If there were no violations of the validation rules a message saying <emphasis role="italic">validation passed successfully</emphasis> is displayed. If there were validation violations they will be presented in a list. The organisation unit, period, left side description and value, operator, and right side value and description for each validation violation are displayed. The show details icon can be clicked in order to get more information about a validation violation. This will open a popup screen that provides information about the data elements included in the validation rules and their corresponding data values. This information can be used in order to correct incorrect data.</para>
      <para>The validation violations can be exported to a PDF document by clicking on the export to PDF button and to a Microsoft Excel workbook by clicking on the export to workbook button.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="stddevoutlierAnalysis">
      <title>Std Dev Outlier Analysis</title>
      <para>The standard deviation based outlier analysis provides a mechanism for revealing values that are numerically distant from the rest of the data. Outliers can occur by chance but they often indicate either measurement error or a heavy-tailed distribution. In the former case one wishes to discard them while in the latter case one should be cautios in using tools or interpretations that assume a normal distribution. The analysis is based on the standard normal distribution.</para>
      <para>First, select the from and to date for the data to include in the analysis. Second, select the data set from which to pick data elements from. Third, select all or some of the data elements in the data set by double-clicking or marking them and clicking the add/remove buttons. Fourth, select the parent organisation unit to use. All children of the organisation unit will be included. Fifth, select the number of standard deviations. This refers to the number of standard devations the data is allowed to deviate from the mean before it is classified as an outlier.</para>
      <para>The possible outlier values discovered will be presented in a list after the analysis process is finished. The data element, organisation unit, period, minimum value, actual value, maximum value will be displayed for each outlier. The minimum and maximum value refers to the border values derived from the number of standard deviations selected for the analysis. Each outlier value can be modified directly in the analysis result page. The value can be modified by clicking inside the corresponding field in the value column, entering a value and then navigate away from that field either by clicking tab or anywhere outside the field. The system will provide an alert if the value is still outside the defined minimum and maximum values, but the value will saved in any case. The field will have a red background color if the value is outside the range, and a green if inside. Each outlier value can be marked for further follow-up by clicking the star icon.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="minmaxoutlierAnalysis">
      <title>Min-Max Outlier Analysis</title>
      <para>The min-max value based outlier analysis provides a mechanism for revealing values that are outside the defined minimum and maximum values. Minimum and maximum values can be custom defined or automatically defined by the system in the data entry module. See section about Std dev outlier analysis for further details on usage.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gapAnalysis">
      <title>Gap Analysis</title>
      <para>The gap analysis provides a mechanism for revealing gaps in the data. A gap exists in the context of a data element and organisation unit. A gap is defined as a period with preceding and succeeding periods which have registered data values, but without registered data values itself. Such a gap might indicate a data capture error or omission and could be further investigated. See section about Std dev outlier analysis for further details on usage.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="followupAnalysis">
      <title>Follow-Up Analysis</title>
      <para>The follow-up analysis function will list all data values which are marked for follup-up. A data value can be marked for follow-up in the data entry module and in the other validation analysis variants in this module. See section about Std dev outlier analysis for further details on usage.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
 
  <chapter>
  <title>Indicators</title>
  <para>When the ‘Data Elements and Indicators’ options is chosen from the main Maintenance menu, the following screen appears:</para>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_element_main.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
  <para>From the left side menu or by scrolling down the central area you can access the various sections on Indicators; </para>
  <para>Indicator, Indicator Type, Indicator Group, Indicator Group Editor, and Indicator Group Set. </para>
  <section>
    <title>Indicator maintenance</title>
    <para>Indicator maintenance functions essentially the same as each of the respective sections in the previous section on data elements. The basic operations will be described in this section, but the reader should  refer to the corresponding sections above for detailed instructions. </para>
    <section id="indicator">
      <title>Indicators</title>
      <para>Indicators are composed of multiple data elements, and typically consist of a numerator and denominator. Indicators are never entered in DHIS2, but are derived from combinations of data elements and factors. Indicators are used to calculate coverage rates, incidence and other values are are a result of data element values that have been entered into the system. </para>
      <para>To access the Indicator maintains page, press Maintenance-&gt;Data element and indicators-&gt;Indicators from the main DHIS2 menu. Similar to data elements, you can add, delete, modify and view extra information about the indicators in the system. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/inidcator_maintainance_main.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Indicators can be filtered by entering the name or a part of the indicator name in the &quot;Filter by name&quot; field. Similar to data elements, indicators can be added by pressing the &quot;Add new&quot; button. Other operations available from this menu are as follows. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/edit.png"/> Existing indicators can be edited. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/i18n.png"/> Translate an existing indicator. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/delete.png"/> Delete an existing indicator. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/dhis2_images/information.png"/> Get detailed information about this indicator. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>To add a new indicator, click the &quot;Add new&quot; button. The following screen is displayed. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="30%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/indicator_add.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Each of the fields marked with an asterisk are compulsory. A description of each field is provided below. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name: The full name of the indicator, such as &quot;Incidence of confirmed malaria cases per 1000 population&quot;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Short name: An abbreviated name of the indicator such as &quot;Inc conf. malaria per 1000 pop&quot;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Alternative name: An additional field for a possible alternative name of the indicator. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Code: In many countries, indicator are often assigned a particular code. This code can be entered here. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Description: A brief, informative description of the indicator and how it is calculated can be entered here. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Annualized: Determines whether or not an annualization factor is applied during the calculation of the indicator. Typically, annualized indicator&apos;s numerator are multiplied by a factor of 12, and the denominator is for instance a yearly population figure. This allows for monthly coverage values to be calculated with yearly population figures.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type: This field will determine a factor that will automatically be applied during the calculation of the indicator. Possible choices are determined by the Indicator Types (described below). For instance, a &quot;Percent&quot; indicator will automatically be multiplied by a factor of 100 when exported to the data mart, so that it will display as a percentage. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>URL: Can be used as a link to an indicator registry, where a full metadata description of the indicator can be made available. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>To define the numerator and denominator, simply press the respective button, and the following dialogue will be displayed. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="50%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/indicator_numerator_denominator.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Essentially, an indicator is a formula that can be composed of multiple data element, constant factors, and mathematical operators. In order to define a new indicator proceed with the following steps.  </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Provide a description of the numerator can be provided in the &quot;Description field&quot;. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the aggregation operator, either as a SUM or COUNT. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Define the formula of the indicator by selecting the data elements that should compose the numerator from the &quot;Data elements&quot; field. Simply select the data element, and double click it. It will now appear in the formula. You formula must be mathematically valid, including the proper use of parentheses when necessary. You can double click on each of the mathematical operator buttons below the indicator formula definition  to add them to your formula. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the Save button to save all changes to the numerator. Click cancel to discard any changes that you have made. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Follow the same procedure in order to define the denominator. </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="indicatorType">
      <title>Indicator types</title>
      <para>Indicator types simply define a factor that will be applied during aggregation. Indicator values that are calculate during a data mart export or report table generation process will appear properly formatted, and will therefore not require an additional multiplier (e.g. 100 in the case of percents) for the values to appear correctly formatted. </para>
      <para>The indicator type maintenance panel has all of the same functions (Add new, Edit, Translate, Delete, and Information) as the Indicator maintenance section. </para>
      <para>There are only two fields that need to be filled-in to create an indicator type, Name and Factor, as seen below. Name refers to the Indicator type (e.g. Per cent, Per thousand, Per ten thousand, etc). The factor is the numeric factor that will be applied during the calculation of the indicator. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="25%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/indicator_type.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section id="indicatorGroup">
      <title>Indicator groups</title>
      <para>Indicator groups function essentially the same as data element groups. Multiple indicators can be assigned to a group for easy filtering and analysis. To assign indicators to groups, simple press Maintenance-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Indicator groups.  See the section on Data element groups for detailed instructions of how to use this module. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="indicatorGroupEditor">
      <title>Indicator group editor</title>
      <para>The indicator group editor module functions essentially the same as the data element group editor module, except on indicators. You can easily rearrange the groups that indicators belong to with this module. To access it, choose To assign indicators to groups, simple press Maintenance-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Indicator group editor from the main menu. See the section on Data element group editor for further instructions. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="indicatorGroupSet">
      <title>Indicator group sets</title>
      <para>Similar to data element group sets, indicator group sets serve to create combined groups of similar indicators. For instance, you might have a group of indicators called &quot;Malaria&quot; and &quot;Leishmaniasis&quot;. Both of these groups could be combined into a group set called &quot;Vector-borne diseases&quot;. Indicator groups sets are used during analysis of data to combine similar themes of indicators. To access this module choose Maintenance-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Indicator group sets from the main menu. The following dialogue will appear. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/indicator_group_sets.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Supply a name for the indicator group set, and then move the desired members from the &quot;Available Indicator Groups&quot; to the &quot;Group members&quot;. Click &quot;Add&quot; to save your changes and &quot;Cancel&quot; to discard any changes. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="dataDictionary">
    <title>Data dictionaries</title>
    <para>Data dictionaries are used to group data elements and indicators during filtering operations. They are useful for combining related groups of data elements and indicators according to the programs to which they belong. For instance a data dictionary called &quot;MCH&quot; could be created, and all maternal and child health data elements and indicators could be added to the dictionary. The data dictionary can be access by choosing Maintenance-&gt;Data elements and indicators-&gt;Data dictionary. The following screen will be displayed in the browser. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_dictionary.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Provide a name for the data dictionary in the &quot;Name&quot; field and a description of its contents. Data elements and indicators can be added or removed from the dictionary. Click &quot;Save&quot; if you are creating a new data dictionary or &quot;Add&quot; if you are editing the contents of an existing data dictionary.   </para>
  </section>
  <section id="translation">
    <title>Translations</title>
    <para>DHIS 2 provides functionality for translations of data element, data element group, indicator, indicator group, and data element category names.  These elements can be translated to any number of locales. A locale  represents a specific geographical, political, or cultural region. </para>
    <para>To add a translation click the Translate icon next to the element you would like to translate. Start by selecting the desired locale from the Locale select box. If your locale is not in the list you need to add it first. Fill in locale language and locale country code. The locale language is a lower-case, two-letter valid ISO Language Code. The locale country is a upper-case, two-letter valid ISO Country Code. Then in the Translate section, select your locale, then enter values for the avaliable element properties. You can select the reference locale, that is the locale the current element is displayed in, from the select box to the right. Translations can be enabled by selecting the desired locale under Database Language under User Settings in the Settings module.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
  
  <chapter>
    <title>Reporting</title>
    <section>
      <title>Reporting options</title>
      <para>The reporting module in DHIS 2 provides a range of reporting alternatives, including canned reports using either JasperReports or BIRT, data set reports, charts, pivot tables and report tables.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Data sources for reporting</title>
      <section id="datamart">
        <title>Data mart</title>
        <para>The purpose of the datamart is to provide pre-processed data to external data analysis and reporting tools. The datamart consists of two tables, aggregateddatavalues and aggregatedindicatorvalues in the DHIS2 database. The values in the datamart are aggregated versions of the raw data found in the datavalue table as well as calculated indicator values.. Aggregation can take place over time (e.g. from monthly data to aggregated quarterly values), or place (e.g. from PHU data to aggregated district totals) and the datamart can store all kinds of such aggregated values. The datamart is as such just a processed &quot;copy&quot; of the data values and it can be emptied and regenerated at any time, and the tables are read only tables. The metadata in the two data mart tables are referenced by internal identifiers, such as dataelementid, organisationunitid which refer to the tables like dataelement and organisationunit, see &apos;How to make use of the data mart in external tools&apos; for more on this. How the data is aggregated and what ends up in these two tables is controlled from the Data mart export user interface under the Services submenu.</para>
        <section>
          <title>The data mart export process</title>
          <section id="datamarthowto">
            <title>How to create a data mart export</title>
            <para>In the Datamart management window click on the Add New button and a Generate data mart window will open. There are 4 selection boxes; Data elements, Indicators, Organisation units, and periods. For each of the boxes select what you want to export, note if you don&apos;t want both data elements and indicators, you can leave one of these empty, but at least on of these need some selected items together with selected orgunits and periods. The available list on the left side can be filtered by data element group, indicator group, organisation unit level, and period type accordingly. You can move items across to the selected list by double clicking on an item in the available list or by selecting an item and use the move buttons (see selection button explanations below). </para>
            <para>When you are done selecting you can export to data mart by clicking on the Export button. If you want to keep your selections for later you can give it a name in the Name text box at the bottom of the window and click on Save. See more about saved data mart exports below. </para>
            <para>Selection buttons </para>
            <para>&gt; will move the selected item across form the available list on the left to the selected list on the right </para>
            <para>&gt;&gt; will move all items in the available list across to the selected list </para>
            <para>&gt;&gt;&gt; only applies to orgunits and will move the children of the selected orgunit across to the selected list </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Orgunit levels</title>
            <para>The datamart can include values aggregated to different levels in the same table and exactly which level a value belongs to is described by the &apos;level&apos; column. When pulling data put of the datamart into external tools it is important to be aware of this level as combining data for different levels will result in duplication. For DHIS 1.4 users this means that there is no longer a separate table per level, but in stead on common table and a level column that separates the levels. Also note that while in 1.4 you specify in the individual data element and indicator definitions to which orgunit levels the datamart should export to, in DHIS2 this is only defined in the datamart export window. So in DHIS2 this is completely decoupled from the data element and indicator definitions and up to any user to define which orgunits (at any level) they want to see aggregated data for. </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Period types/ data frequencies</title>
            <para>The datamart can hold values aggregated to different period types or frequencies, e.g. monthly, quarterly or yearly data. The &apos;periodtypeid&apos; refers to the frequency the value belongs to, and the periodis column refers to the exact period, e.g. the periodtype can be &apos;monthly&apos; and the period be &apos;Jan-2010&apos;. Again be careful in combining values with different periodtypes as this will cause duplication. </para>
            <para>Which orgunits that get exported to datamart (the two tables agggregateddatavalue and aggregatedindicatorvalue) are ONLY controlled through the datamart export window, and there you define this per orgunit, not per orgunit level. There is a filter using orgunit level, but the orgunits that are selected are the only ones that end up in the datamart. Same for data elements and indicators. </para>
            <para>Every time you do a datamart you can change which orgunits to export data for. The data values will automatically be aggregated up to the orgunit that is selected, no matter what level. </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Data element categories in the data mart</title>
            <para>Each data value for a data element has a reference to a category option combo, which is a combination of the disaggregations for the data value, e.g. (male,&lt;5y) or (In PHU, &lt;1y). These disaggregations are exported as they are to the data mart, and no aggregation is done on this dimension. See the data elements section for more on data element categories and the resource tables section for more information on how to do aggregation on these categories.</para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Limitation to the number of data elements per export</title>
            <para>Due to the limitation in number of columns per table in the database there is a limit to how many data elements that can be selected per data mart export. In postgres this limot is 255 (need to verify this number) data elements. If you need to export more than this number of data elements you have to split it up into multiple data mart exports and run them one by one.</para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Adding new data to an existing data mart</title>
            <para>When you add new data to an existing data mart the new values will be appended to the existing so that the data mart grows for each new process if new selections (such as new periods) have been made. If any of the selected values are already in the data mart then the old will be replaced by the newly generated values. </para>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Saved data mart exports</title>
          <para>To simplify this selection process you can save a datamart export, which basically means saving the selected items (not the data) so that you can run the same at a later point without re-selecting everything. New months need to be added though, while orgunits, data elements and indicators usually stay the same.</para>
          <para>RELATIVE PERIODS IN DATAMART -NEW!!</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Routinely data mart export procedures</title>
          <para>RELATIVE PERIODS IN DATAMART -NEW!!</para>
          <para>In a monthly data entry cycle the typical work routine would be to run all the datamart exports after the data entry process has been finalised. For each of the saved datamarts you would typically select the current reporting month and export only for that period to add the newly registered values (and aggregates based on these) to the existing data mart. If any backlog data has been entered or values for previous period have been corrected since the last data mart export then these periods also need to be added. E.g. in Sierra Leone they have set up a series of saved data mart exports: - PHU all indicators - Chiefdom (subdistrict) all indicators - District all indicators - PHU morbidity and mortality raw data - PHU EPI and nutrition raw data - PHU HIV data - PHU RCH data - Chiefdom Morbidity and Mortality data - etc. These exports are then run every month when there is new data. Each saved export is opened one by one, the new period added and the export run. </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Resource tables</title>
        <para>Resource tables provide additional information about the dimensions of the data in a format that is well suited for external tools to combine with the data mart tables. By joining the data mart with these resource tables one can easily aggregate along the data element category dimension or data element/indicator/organisation unit groups dimensions. E.g. by tagging all the data values with the category option male or female and provide this in a separate column &apos;gender&apos; one can get subtotals of male and female based on data values that are collected for category option combinations like (male, &lt;5) and (male,&gt;5). See the Pivot Tables section for more examples of how these can be used. orgunitstructure is another important table in the database that helps to provide the hierarchy of orgunits together with the data. By joining the orgunitstructure table with the data mart tables you can get rows of data values with the full hierarchy, e.g. on the form: OU1, OU2, OU3, OU4, DataElement, Period, Value (Sierra Leone, Bo, Badija, Ngelehun CHC, BCG &lt;1, Jan-10, 32) This format makes it much easier for e.g. pivot tables or other OLAP tools to aggregate data up the hierarchy. </para>
      </section>
      <section id="reportTable">
        <title>Report tables</title>
        <para>Report tables are meant to be database tables fulfilling the specific data needs of a report, chart, pivot table or other output format. It can be understood as a mini datamart that contains only the data needed for its purpose (the report). The rationale behind this concept is to automatically provide the data sources for reports without bothering the users every time, like a normal datamart, and to speed up the data processing and aggregation (small targeted datamarts are obviously faster than big ones). When created and generated a report table will appear in the DHIS 2 database as a normal table, but always with the prefix _report. This table should not be altered manually as it is controlled by the system. These tables are constantly being deleted and recreated as the user wants new updated data within the same table structure. These tables can then be access and used from any third party tool for displaying data. In DHIS 2 we have integrated with the BIRT report designer from the Eclipse platform and made it especially easy to link BIRT reports to report tables and to run these reports from within DHIS 2. However, we see report tables as a much broader tool and concept than to just support BIRT reports. It can and should (for performance gain and automation) be used for as many data output purposes as possible. e.g. as data sources for the database views used for Excel pivot tables. </para>
        <para> A report tables is a data source that can be defined once and then run automatically in the background when a report needs new and updated data. Standard reports (BIRT or Jasper) are directly linked to one or more report tables and these are then automatically processed in the background when the report is run. Report parameters are added to the report tables to make these generic and reusable over time or across different orgunits. </para>
        <section>
          <title>How to create report tables</title>
          <para>To create a new report table click on one of the 4 Add buttons in the top right corner.</para>
          <section>
            <title>Data Element and Indicator tables</title>
            <para>These two tables types are very similar with the only difference being that one has data element values and the other indicator values.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Cross tab dimensions</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>You can cross-tab one or more of the following dimensions: data element/indicator, orgunit, and period, which means that columns will be created based on the values of the dimensions chosen, e.g. if indicators is selected you will get column names in the table reflecting the names of the selected indicators. You must select at least 1 dimension for the table to be valid. Selecting all 3 is possible, but makes little sense.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Include regression</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>This adds additional columns with regression values that can be included in the report design, e.g. in line charts.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Indicators/Data elements</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Here you select the data elements/indicators that you want to include in the report. Use the group filter to more easily find what you are looking for and double click on the items you want to include.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Organisation Units</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Here you can either opt for selecting some fixed/static orgunits to always include in the report, or to keep this section empty and let the users select orgunits when running the report through the use of report parameters (see further down).</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Periods</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Here you can either choose fixed periods that you always want to include in the report or leave this section empty and opt for relative periods in stead.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Relative periods</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>In stead of using fixed/static periods like &apos;Jan-2010&apos; or &apos;Q1-2010&apos; more generic periods can be used to create reusable report tables, e.g. for monthly reports the period &apos;reporting month&apos; will simply pick the current reporting month selected by the user when running the report. Here is a description of the possible relative periods: </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Reporting month:</emphasis> Use this for monthly reports. The month selected in the reporting month parameter will be used in the report. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Last 3/6/9/12 months:</emphasis> Relative to the selected reporting month the aggregated value for the previous 3,6,9,or 12 months will be used. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Last 3-6, 6-9, 9-12 months:</emphasis> Used for &quot;rolling quarters&quot; reports. Aggregated 3 months values will be used based on the selected reporting month. E..g if July 2010 is selected the last 3-6 period will be an aggregated period of Feb-April 2010. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Last 12 individual months:</emphasis> Use this for monthly trend analysis. This will give 12 values, one for each of the 12 previous months relative to the chosen reporting month. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">So far this year:</emphasis> This is the cumulative so far in the year, aggregating the months from the beginning of the year up to and including the selected reporting month. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">So far this financial year:</emphasis> Similar to the above, but a cumulative value relative to start of the financial year to the selected reporting month. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Individual months/quarter this year</emphasis>: This will provide one value per month or quarter in the year. This is well suited for standard monthly or quarterly reports where all month/quarters need to be listed. Periods that still have no data will be empty, but always keep the same column name.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Reporting parameters</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Report parameters make the reports more generic and reusable over time and for different orgunits. These parameters will pop up when generating the report table or running a report based on the report table and the users will select what they want to see in the report. There are three possible report parameters, and you can select to use none, 1, 2 or all 3 parameters. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Reporting month:</emphasis> This decides which fixed periods that will be fetched for chosen relative periods. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Parent organisation unit:</emphasis> Select the parent of all the orgunit children you want listed in the report. E.g. a selected district will trigger the use of all sub-districts in that selected district. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Organisation unit:</emphasis> This triggers the use of this orgunit in the report. No children are listed. </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Data element dimension tables</title>
            <para>These tables enable the use of data element categories in report tables. One category combination per report. Subtotals and the total will also be included in the table, e.g. a gender(male,female)+EPI age(&lt;1,&gt;1 category combo would give the following columns: male+&lt;1, male+&gt;1, Female+&lt;1, female+&gt;1, male, female,&lt;1, &gt;1, total. </para>
            <para>Only data elements from the same category combination can be included. </para>
            <para>All cross tab dimensions are disabled since the columns are the various disaggregations from the category combination. </para>
            <para>Orgunit, periods and parameters as in the data element/indicator tables. </para>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Using report tables</title>
          <para>To make the report tables reusable over time and across orgunits they can have \ parameters. Three types of parameters are allowed; orgunit, parent orgunit (for listing of orgunits in one area) and reporting month. As a side note I can mention that we are looking into expanding this to include reporting quarter and year, or to make that period parameter more generic with regard to period type somehow. Be able to use period as a parameter makes the report table reusable over time and as such fits nicely with report needs such as monthly, quarterly or annual reports. When a report is run by the user in the DHIS 2 the user must specify the values for the report tables that are linked to the report, and first the report table is re-generated (deleted and re-created with updated data) and then the report is run (in BIRT report engine). </para>
          <para>Report tables can consist of either values related to data elements or indicators, and not a mix of the two. A third report table type is data completeness, which is related to completeness of reporting across orgunits for a given month. Completeness reports will be covered in a separate section. The reason for not mixing data elements and indicators in one report table is due to the cross tab functionality that would be very complex and less useful with yet another dimension. Since two or more report tables can easily be linked to one report this limitation should not have much effect on report design possibilities. </para>
          <para>There are three dimensions in a report table that identify the data; indicators or data elements, orgunits and periods. For each of these dimensions the user can select which metadata values to include in the report. The user must select one or more data elements or indicators to appear in the report. The orgunit selection can be substituted with a parameter, wither one specific orgunit or an orgunit parent (making all its children appear in the report). If one or more orgunits are selected and no orgunit parameter is used then the report is static with regard to which orgunits to include, which in most cases is an unnecessary restriction to a report.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Using relative periods</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>The period selection is more advanced as it can in addition to specific periods like Jan-09, Q1-08, 2007 also contain what is called relative periods. As report usually is run routinely over time a specific period like Jan-09 is not very useful in a report. In stead, if you want to design a monthly report you could use the relative period called Reporting Month. Then you must also include Reporting Month as one of your report parameters to let the system know what exactly is the Reporting Month on the time of report generation. There are many other relative periods available and they all relate to the report parameter Reporting Month. E.g. the relative period called So far this year refers to the accumulative value for the year incl. the Reporting Month. If you want a trend report with multiple periods in stead of one aggregated period you can select e.g. Individual Months this year which would give you values for each month so far in the year, and you can do a similar report with quarters. The idea is to support as many generic report types as possible using relative periods, so if you have other report needs please suggest new relative periods on the mailing list and they will be added to the report table options.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Cross-tabbing dimensions</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>Cross tabbing is a very powerful functionality in report design as the typical DHIS data table with references to period, data element/indicator and orgunit makes more advanced report design very difficult as you cannot put e.g. specific indicators, periods or orgunits on specific columns. E.g. by cross-tabbing on the indicator dimension in an indicator report table you will get the indicator names on the column headers in you report, in addition to a column referencing orgunit, and another column referencing period. With such a table design you could drag and drop indicator names to specific columns or chart positions in the BIRT report design. Similarly you can cross tab on orgunits or periods to make their names specifically available to report design. E.g. by cross-tabbing on periods and selecting the two relative periods, reporting month and so far this year you can design reports with both the last month and the accumulative annual value for given month as they will be available as column headers in your report table. It is also possible to combine two dimensions in cross-tabbing, e.g. period and indicator, which makes it possible to e.g. look at three selected indicators for two specific relative periods. This would e.g. make it possible to make a table or chart based report with BCG, DPT3 and Measles coverage, both for the last month and the accumulative coverage so far in the year. </para>
          <para>All in all, by combining the functionality of cross tabbing, relative periods and report table parameters you should have a tool to support most report scenarios. If not we would be very happy to receive suggestions to further improvements to report tables. As already mentioned we have started to look at more fine-grained parameters for the period dimension as the Reporting Month does not cover or at least is not intuitive enough when it comes to e.g. quarterly reports. </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="standardreport">
      <title>Standard Reports</title>
      <para/>
      <section>
        <title>How to set up and run standard reports</title>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Add a new standard report:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>In Reports module, go to Reports-&gt;Standard Reports and click the left side &apos;Add new&apos; button. Provide a name for the report, upload your design file (.rptdesign) and select the report table(s) you have used in your report. Then Save.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Running standard reports: (NEED TO BE UPDATED FOR 2.0.5)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>You access the available reports from the Services drop-down menu, by selecting Reports. In the report menu in the left bar, click Standard Report. A list of all pre-defined reports will appear in the main window. </para>
        <para>SCREENSHOT1</para>
        <para/>
        <para>Here two reports are shown; one called ANC by fixed/outreach, and another called ANC visit coverage.</para>
        <para>SCREENSHOT 2</para>
        <para>The operations buttons for each report are, from left to right; </para>
        <para>-Generate data source and view report: Click this to select report parameters and view report.</para>
        <para>-View report based on existing datasource: Click this to show the report without changing report parameters </para>
        <para>-Edit reports: Change name, design template, and report tables </para>
        <para>-Add to dashboard: Include this report in the list of reports available from the dashboard </para>
        <para>-Delete report </para>
        <para>In most cases, you would like to select report parameters and view the report. You do this by clicking the first button from the left. </para>
        <para>Each report can have up to three report parameters; Reporting month, Parent Organization unit, and Organization Unit. The reporting month determines the month you want the report to calculate the relative periods of that report from. A report can for example include the reporting month, summary totals for the last 3 months, 6 months, quarterly so far this year, etc, and the reporting month determines which time periods are included in these. The parent orgunit parameter can be used to see a limited set of orgunits. Only the children of the parent unit will be included in the report. The last possible parameter is the orgunit, which is simply the orgunit the report will include. </para>
        <para>The report called ANC by fixed/outreach has two reporting parameters, namely reporting month and organization unit. Thus we can set the reporting month and organization unit (you can select from which level to list the possible options) when we click on the button furthest to the left. </para>
        <para>As an example we do this, and select July 2009 and Moyamba district, as in the figure below.</para>
        <para>SCREENSHOT 3</para>
        <para>Click OK to generate the report. After a little while, a new window will appear with the report for the given report parameters, as shown in the figure below.</para>
        <para>SCREENSHOT 4</para>
        <para>This report has been defined to show a table of ANC visits by fixed, outreach, and total, for one month (the reporting month), and one organization unit (which we selected to be Moyamba district). It also shows the data in a chart. The other report is slightly different. It too has the report parameters reporting month and organization unit, in the example below set to July 2009 and Sierra Leone. </para>
        <para>SCREENSHOT 5</para>
        <para>The resulting report contains the same table, but a chart showing the ANC coverages (based on expected number of pregnancies) instead of the chart of just the raw figures. </para>
        <para>SCREENSHOT 6</para>
        <para>Note that you can select to view these reports again without selecting new report parameters. Just click the icon second from left, and the report will appear with the last selected report parameters.</para>
        <para>SCREENSHOT 7</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>DHIS 2 Excel Reporting</title>
    <para>A key requirement of a health information system is that the information contained in the system is available in many different formats that are familiar to the end-users. Many health information personnel are familiar with standard office productivity packages such as <productname>Microsoft Office</productname> or OpenOffice. Production of reports in Excel format allows health workers to submit reports to managers and other persons that may not have access to the HMIS, or lack training in its use. Excel offers the capability to deliver powerful, user-friendly reports to many different clients of the information system.</para>
    <para>Users, especially health workers, can use DHIS 2 easily with the new Excel reporting tool developed by HISP Vietnam team. This module has been based on HISP India teams ideas and technologies. The module has subsequently been merged into the main DHIS2 application. This reporting tool with Excel output files uses less memory and is comparatively faster when compared to other reporting modules</para>
    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/administration_page.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
    </screenshot>
    <section>
      <title>Administration</title>
      <para>There are six function of this module.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Configuration</emphasis>: Set a path to the directory where the excel template files are stored.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">List of reports</emphasis>: Allows users to create reports and its items and to assign the organisation units or the organisation unit groups to the reports. There are four types of report, as follows: a report containing standard data elements, a report listing organisation unit groups as rows, a report listing period of time as columns, a report generating data elements combined with categories</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Data Entry Status</emphasis> (or view the status of the data entry): View the data entry status to know about data entered, reports finished or not finished yet with data entry. In order to view the data entry status, adding data sets which is equivalent to the data entry is mandatory. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Excel items</emphasis>: In many situations, health workers in the field may not have good Internet access, and will therefore need to enter data &quot;offline&quot; and transmit this data via email or other means, for subsequent importation into the DHIS database. The Excel Report data import feature allows users to import data from a pre-designed Excel templates directly into the DHIS database automatically. Alternatively, selected elements may be imported. It supports three types of report, includes a report containing standard data elements, a report listing organisation unit groups as rows, a report generating data elements combined with categories.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Excel Template Management</emphasis> : Manage Template Excel files which are used to export reports, includes upload, download, delete and rename files.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Clean temporary directory</emphasis>: Every time a user generates a report, the system creates an Excel file in the temporary directory (<envar>excelreporttemplate</envar> directory). This directory would be larger and larger after some time and occupy a lot of memory. This function will clean those files from temporary directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section id="excelReportingConfiguration">
        <title>Configuration</title>
        <para>The directory configuration is to set the path of the directory containing the Excel Template (.xls) file. </para>
        <para>In order to set the directory, choose <emphasis role="bold">Administrator &gt; Configuration&gt;</emphasis> Set path and specify the path. The procedure is outlined in more detail below. </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> to open Administrator page.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/configure_directory.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Configuration</emphasis> button</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Set a path to the folder containing excel file </para>
            <para>An Excel template directory is simply a directory that will be used to contain all the necessary files. It is recommended to create this folder inside the <envar>DHIS2_HOME</envar> folder. </para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/configure_directory1.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> to save</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingListOfReports">
        <title>List of reports </title>
        <para>The function allows users to create reports and its items and to assign the organisation units or the organisation unit groups to the reports</para>
        <section>
          <title>Types of report</title>
          <para>Before generating reports, there is a need to create Excel report template files. Reports will be generated in a standard format according to the structure defined in the template. Currently, there are four report types that the module can support.</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard reports contain default data elements and indicators</emphasis>
              </para>
              <para>Standard reports have a fixed model in which number of the columns and the rows are unchangeable. Normally, this report is generated by only one organisation unit or one organisation unit group at a specified period of time. An example is show below.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/standard_report_template.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Row-based reports with multiple organisational</emphasis>
              </para>
              <para>This type of report displays data elements name in the fixed columns, and organisation units are be displayed automatically according to the selected parents organisation unit in a period of time. These organisation units are also grouped together following the administrative level, such as: province, district, commune, etc.</para>
              <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/list_org_unit_group_report_template.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Reports list time periods in the columns</emphasis>
              </para>
              <para>This report display data values according to the fixed data element names, and the list of time periods are displayed automatically.<screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/list_time_period_report_template.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Reports with data elements and categories</emphasis>
              </para>
              <para>This type of report displays data values which are combined of data elements and category combination. Data element names display as rows and category options are displayed as columns. Data elements names, codes may be displayed automatically as well as the sequence numbers of the rows</para>
              <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/dataelement_category_report_template.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
              </screenshot>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Create a new report in DHIS2 with Excel report template file</title>
          <para>When the Excel report template file is available, creating a new report and the relevant report items are required. A step-by-step procedure is provided below.</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>To create a new report, choose <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">List Of Report</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> --&gt; Fill the information form --&gt; OK</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>To create report items in the report choose <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">List Of Report</emphasis> --&gt; Choose a report --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Report Item</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> --&gt; Fill information form --&gt; OK</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
          <section>
            <title>Create new report </title>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">List Of Reports</emphasis></para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/create_new_report.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Add new report: Click Add button to add new report</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/add_new_report_button.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Fill information of report in this form:</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/enter_report_information.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> *: Enter Name of report</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Excel Template</emphasis>*: Enter name of Excel report template file. (include extension) </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Report Type *: Choose report type </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Normal : to create reports include just data elements or indicator</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Category : to create reports with data values are combined of data elements and categories </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Period column listing: to create reports which list data values according to time period of specified organisation unit.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Organisation unit listing: reports which list data values according to organisation units.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Period position row and Period position column: Row and Column Number in Excel template file where to put Period value.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Organisation Unit Row and Organisation Unit Column: Row and Column Number in Excel template file where to put Organisation Unit Name.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click OK button to create new report</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/list_of_reports.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>There are buttons that can be used for various actions as depicted below: </para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/operating_buttons.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Report Associations <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/association_org_unit.jpg"/>for assigning reports to organisation units</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Report Item <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/report_item.jpg"/>for creating report items in the report</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Remove <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/remove_report.jpg"/>for removing report</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Edit <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/edit_report.jpg"/>for editing reports information.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Organisation unit Group <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/assign_org_unit_group.jpg"/>: For choose which organisation group would be list in the report. This button only appear when the Report Type is Organisation Unit Listing</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Data element groups <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/assign_data_element_group.jpg"/> : This button for create Data element group and these groups of data elements would be list in the report. This button only available when report type is Category. </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Create report items</title>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Create Report Item</emphasis> button</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/create_item.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> button to open a form</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/report_item_function.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Fill the report items information</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/enter_report_item_infor.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Name*: Enter report item name (Ex: Total person joined HIA)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Item Type*: Chose item types </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Data element : if this report item is data element</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Indicator: : if this report item is indicator</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Excel formula: if this item describes the excel formula</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Data element Name: if report item is list of data elements names</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Data element Code: If report item is list of data elements codes</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Serial : If report item is list of auto generating sequence no</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Organisation: if report item is list of organisation unit.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Period Type*: Chose period type which data values of that report item would be aggregated and displays according to period parameter that user will choose when generate report. (Last 3 months, Last 6 months, So far this year, Quarterly, Six-Monthly, Yearly).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Expression *: Click Expression button to choose Data element, Indicator, Or just type excel formula if Item type is Excel formula.</para>
                <screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/create_expression.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot>
                <screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/create_expression1.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot>
                <para>The category option would be <emphasis role="italic">default</emphasis> if data element hasnt been combined with any category combo. Other options are described below:</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Sheet No*: type sheet no where this report item would be display in excel template file</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Row*: row number refers to cell where report item would be display in Excel file.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Column*: column number refers to cell where report item would be display in Excel file.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click OK button to create report item.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/new_report_item.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>New report item has been created</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/NewReportItem.jpg" width="60%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <tip>
              <para>There must be at least one period type in a report.</para>
            </tip>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Copy selected items to</emphasis> button: To copy the report items to excel items of an excel item group<orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>From list of reports page, Add new report</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>From source report, select report items need to be copied.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Copy selected items to</emphasis> button</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="italic">List of report</emphasis>: chose a destination report</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="italic">Sheet No</emphasis>: Choose the Sheet No which report Item would be display.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to copy</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist><screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/copy_report_item.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
              </screenshot><tip>
                <para>Copy selected items to other reports for quickly developing many reports with the same data elements but with the different periods.</para>
              </tip><emphasis role="bold">Copy to excel items</emphasis> button: To copy the report items when the new report has an item which can be reused from the existing report. </para>
            <para>
              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>From source report, select report items need to be copied.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Copy to excel items</emphasis> button</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="italic">List of groups</emphasis>: chose a destination report</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="italic">Sheet No</emphasis>: Choose the Sheet No which report Item would be display.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to copy</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
              <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/copy_to_excel_iems_group.png" align="center"/>
              </screenshot>
              <tip>
                <para>Copy selected items to Excel item groups for quickly developing many groups with the same data elements.</para>
              </tip>
            </para>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Assign report </title>
          <section>
            <title>Assign report to Org Units </title>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Report Associations</emphasis> button:</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/report_association.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Chose Org Units to assign and click Save button</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/select_org_unit.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Select Org Unit groups which would be available in the report by clicking on each organisational unit. <!--This is not clear. Rephrase. -->There is a difference between Select Org Units to assign to report for OrgUnit generate reports later, which select org unit groups are list of OrgUnit groups would be available in reports.</para>
            <para>This function only appears in <emphasis role="bold">Organization Unit Listing</emphasis> report type. </para>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Organisation Unit group</emphasis> button.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/select_org_unit_group.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Select Organisation unit groups, arrange sequence of these groups, and click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> to save.</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/select_org_unit_group1.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Assign report to user role</title>
            <para>To manage the authority of using the reports, we should assign reports to user roles. This allows the administrator to decide which users are able to view certain reports.</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>From <emphasis role="bold">Main</emphasis> menu, choose <emphasis role="bold">Maintenance</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis role="bold">Users</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>From Left menu, chose User Role</para>
                <screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/assign_user_role.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> button to edit User roles information</para>
                <screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/edit_user_role.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Select Excel reports, click <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to assign excel reports to user role.</para>
                <screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/select_excel_report.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingDataEntryStatus">
        <title>Data Entry Status</title>
        <para>This function allows users to see which datasets are entered with data and how the data values are entered. This helps save time for the health manager to follow the completeness of the data entered. In particular, there is a need of viewing data set entry status.</para>
        <para>Add data set to view</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/data_entry_status.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Entry Status</emphasis> page would be displayed. Click <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> button to add data set.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/add_dataset.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Select the desired data set and Organisation Unit from the menu.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/add_dataset1.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingExcelItems">
        <title>Excel items</title>
        <para>The sub function allows users to import data from a pre-designed Excel templates directly into the DHIS database automatically. Alternatively, selected elements may be imported.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/excel_item_group.png" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <section>
          <title>Create a template to import</title>
          <para><orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>To create a group, choose <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> --&gt;<emphasis role="bold"> Excel items</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Add </emphasis>--&gt; Fill the information form --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>To create items in the grorp, choose <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Excel items</emphasis> --&gt; Choose a group --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Excel items </emphasis>--&gt; Fill information form -&gt; <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>Creating a Excel items group which contains Excel items. A Excel item correspond with a data cell into imputted template Excel files. A step-by-step procedure is provided below.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/add_excel_item_group.png" align="center"/>
          </screenshot>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Name </emphasis>*: Enter Name of report.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Report Type </emphasis>*: Choose report type<itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">Normal</emphasis> : to create group include just data elements or indicator</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">Category</emphasis> : to create group with data values are combined of data elements and categories</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">Organisation unit listing </emphasis>: groups which list data values according to organisation units.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="italic">Period Type </emphasis>*: Type of period to import data values.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to create new report.</para>
          <para>There are buttons that can be used for various actions as depicted below.</para>
          <screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/operations_excel_item_group.png" align="center"/>
          </screenshot>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para> Associations <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/association_org_unit.jpg"/>for assigning a group to organisation units.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Excel item group <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/report_item.jpg"/>for creating report items in the report.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Remove <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/remove_report.jpg"/>for removing excel item group.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Edit <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/edit_report.jpg"/>for editing information of group.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Organisation unit Group <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/assign_org_unit_group.jpg"/> for choose which organisation group would be list in the group. This button only appear when the Group Type is Organisation Unit Listing</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Data element groups <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/assign_data_element_group.jpg"/> for create Data element group and these groups of data elements would be list in the report. This button only available when report type is Category. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Create excel items</title>
          <para>Click<emphasis role="bold"> Excel item</emphasis> buttton <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/report_item.jpg"/>to create items.</para>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> button to open a form.<screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/add_excel_item.png" align="center"/>
            </screenshot></para>
          <para>Fill information of an excel items.<itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Name*: Enter item name</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Expression *: Click Expression button to choose Data element, Indicator, Or just type excel formula if Item type is Excel formula.</para>
                <screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/create_expression.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot>
                <screenshot>
                  <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/create_expression1.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
                </screenshot>
                <para>The category option would be <emphasis role="italic">default</emphasis> if data element hasnt been combined with any category combo. Other options are described below:</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Sheet No*: type sheet no where this item would be display in excel template file</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Row*: row number refers to cell where item would be display in Excel file.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Column*: column number refers to cell where item would be display in Excel file.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to create item.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Copy selected items to</emphasis> button: To copy the report items when the new report has an item which can be reused from the existing report<screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/copy_excel_item_to.png" align="center"/>
            </screenshot><orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>From List of groups page, select items need to be copied.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Copy selected items to</emphasis> button.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">List of groups</emphasis>: chose a destination report.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Sheet No</emphasis>: Choose the Sheet No which report Item would be display.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to copy.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
          <tip>
            <para>Copy selected items to other groups for quickly developing many groups with the same data elements but with the different periods</para>
          </tip>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingExcelTemplateManagement">
        <title>Excel Template Management </title>
        <para>This is used to manage Template Excel files which are used to export reports, includes upload, download, delete and rename files.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/excel_template_management.png" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <para>To upload template file, choose <emphasis role="bold">Browse</emphasis> button.<screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/upload_template_excel_file.png" align="center"/>
          </screenshot></para>
        <para>Choose a file from shown dialog<screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/choose_upload_file.png" align="center"/>
          </screenshot></para>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Open</emphasis> to choose file, and click <emphasis role="bold">Upload</emphasis> button to upload. If to upload successfully, a message shown :<screenshot>
            <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/upload_success.png" align="center"/>
          </screenshot><tip>
            <para>No upload if the chosen file is not excel file.</para>
          </tip></para>
        <para>There three operation functions</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Remove <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/remove_report.jpg"/>For removing report</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Edit <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/edit_report.jpg"/>for editing reports information.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Download <inlinegraphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/download_template_excel_file.png" align="center"/> for dowloading template file. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingCleanTemporaryDirectory">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="italic">Clean temporary directory</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>This allows the user to clean temporary directory.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>From <emphasis role="bold">Main</emphasis> menu, choose <emphasis role="bold">Maintenance</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis role="bold">Clean temporary directory </emphasis></para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/clean temporary directory.png" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Generate Report</title>
      <para>There are six functions of this module.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Generate Report</emphasis>: Allow users to generate reports according to parameters such as time period, organisation unit, organisation unit group and to generate group of reports to many sheets of a single Excel file.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Generate advanced report</emphasis>: Generates reports by OrgUnit group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Import excel files</emphasis>: Imports data values from an Excel file to the DHIS database.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Data Set completed reports</emphasis>: Generates the report which show status of completeness of entering data .</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Data entry Status</emphasis>: View data entry status.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Individual reports</emphasis>: Generate user defined reports which list data elements and a list of periods which can be chosen by the user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section id="excelReportingReport">
        <title>Generate report</title>
        <para>To generate a report we just follow these simple steps. </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click Generate Report</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select Org Unit</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select report Group </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select Report from list</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select period</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select period</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click Generate Report button</para>
            <screenshot>
              <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/generate_report.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingAdvancedReport">
        <title>Generate advanced report</title>
        <para>This <emphasis role="italic">Generate Advanced Report</emphasis> function allow users to generate a report according to the parameters such as: <emphasis role="italic">Report group name</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Report name</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">selected period</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic">organisation unit</emphasis><emphasis role="italic">group name</emphasis>. The difference between <emphasis role="italic">Generate Advanced Report</emphasis> function and <emphasis role="italic">Generate Report</emphasis> function is that the advanced function is capable of generating reports according to groups of Org Units withing the same level as depicted below.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/advanced_generate_report.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingImportData">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="bold">Import excel files</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>This feature is current still in development. More information on this feature will be added soon. </para>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">EXCEL REPORTING</emphasis> module is continuing develop and the documentation of it for users will be updated. If there is any other type of report template which are not supported by DHIS, feel free to send the requirements. All feedback will be appreciated, please inform us at <emphasis role="underline">
            <email>dhis2-documenters@lists.launchpad.net</email>
          </emphasis>.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingDataSetCompleteReport">
        <title>Data set complete reports</title>
        <para>When users finish entering data for a data set, they need to click the <emphasis role="bold">COMPLETE</emphasis> button to identify that the data set is completely entered. The View Data set complete report function takes care of this completeness. There are two ways of viewing data set complete reports: View as Period or Dataset. When viewing by Period, users can see complete status of 1 dataset in many periods of time. When view by Dataset , users can see many data sets in only a specified period. This function is only used for management users in the upper Organisation Unit. </para>
        <para>To view data set complete reports, do steps below</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>From the left menu, click Dataset complete reports</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose Orgunit name. (Parent Organisation Units)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select Period Type</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select View Type.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select data set (Select only 1 data set if view by Period)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select Period (Select only 1 period if view by Dataset)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click View Report button</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/view_data_set_completed_report.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Example of view report by Period</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/view_data_set_completed_report_period.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Example of view report by data set</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/view_data_set_completed_report_dataset.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingDataEntryStatusReport">
        <title>Data entry status report</title>
        <para>This function allows users to see which datasets are entered with data and how the data values are entered. This helps save time for the health manager to follow the completeness of the data entered. In particular, there is a need of viewing data set entry status.</para>
        <para>View Data entry status</para>
        <para>From Left menu, click Data Entry Status &gt; Select Org Unit name to view.</para>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/data_entry_status1.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <para>The Data entry status is displayed as percentage. The relative percentage of data elements that were entered in the form. </para>
      </section>
      <section id="excelReportingIndividualReport">
        <title>Generate an individual report</title>
        <para>This function allows users to generate the reports with data elements and a list of period as their individual decision. Another way, user can generate a dirty report by selecting data elements, periods to generate a simple excel report without excel template file or creating report or report items. Then, user can bookmark this report for generating later. The steps to generate individual report are listed below</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click Individual report function from the left menu</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select organisation unit</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select data elements</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select category option of selected data element</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click select button</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select period type</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select periods</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click select button</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click generate report button</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click Book mark button for generate later</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/generate_individual_report1.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="resources/images/ExcelReportModule/generate_individual_report.jpg" width="80%" align="center"/>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
 
  <chapter>
  <title>GIS</title>
  <section>
    <title>OpenHealthMapper</title>
    <para>The DHIS 2 GIS web module is inspired by the <ulink url="http://www.who.int/health_mapping/tools/healthmapper/en/">WHO HealthMapper</ulink> desktop application.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Setting up the GIS module</title>  
  <section id="gisSetup">
    <title>Importing geographical layers for orgunit thematic mapping</title>
    <para>The maps are generated off the coordinates information linked to the Organisation Units in the database. No additional files are needed. As soon as the orguints have coordinates the maps will be available in the GIS module. Although it is possible to add/edit coordinates directly in the Edit Organisation Unit window (in Maintenance-&gt;Organisation Unit) we recommend doing this in a batch job using the general import process in  the import/export module. The import process will need a gml file with at least the  two properties; &quot;Name&quot; and &quot;coordinates&quot;.</para>
    <para>To generate the gml file start by installing the open source ogr2ogr tool. This should be available for most Linux distros (e.g. &quot;apt-get install
ogr2ogr&quot;). For Windows, get FWTools, http://fwtools.maptools.org/</para>
    <para>The most common format for GIS data is the ESRI shapefile, which consists of three identically named files with extensions .shp, .shx and .dbf.
(You can use ogr2ogr to convert between any formats, see example below). Open the .dbf in a spreadsheet application (e.g. MS Excel). Make sure 
 there is a field (column) called Name which has Orgunit names, and that these Orgunits are already existing in DHIS2. Also make sure all spellings are identical since the matching is done on this name.
</para>
    <para>On Windows, open the FWTools Shell and navigate to the folder with the shapefile. Issue the following command (replace &quot;output&quot; and
&quot;input&quot; with the actual names):
    <programlisting><userinput> ogr2ogr -F GML output.gml input.shp </userinput></programlisting> 
</para>
    <para>The column in the .dbf file with the orgunit name will have been converted to an XML element inside the GML file. Open the GML file in
a text editor (e.g. Notepad++) and do a search/replace to make sure this element is called exactly ogr:Name (case sensitive), e.g.
&lt;ogr:Name&gt;Badjia&lt;/ogr:Name&gt;
</para>
    <para>Import the GML file into DHIS2 through the import process in the import/export module (under services menu). There is no need to zip the file. Change import Type to Preview before doing the import to see which changes that will be made and resolve any issues with orgunit name matching etc. See the import/export chapter in the manual for more details on import processes. After import the coordinates will be added to the orgunit&apos;s metadata and also be available from the Orgunit Edit window (Maintenance-&gt;Organisation Units).</para>
  </section>
</section>
    
  <section>
    <title>Administering the GIS module</title>
    <section id="gisAdministration">
      <title>Administrator settings</title>
      <para>The administrator settings window can be opened from the map toolbar, click on the wrench symbol (tooltip says Administrator settings). Here you can define the Date Type used to select periods. Either use fixed periods corresponding to the periods used in DHIS data collection (weeks, months, quarters, 6-months, years etc.) or use the more flexible start and end dates.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisOverlay">
      <title>Register overlays</title>
      <para>Overlays are geographical layers that do not have any direct linkage
    to data in the database. Example include roads, rivers, airports, ports,
    and other geographical information that you may want to display on your
    map, but that is not neccsarily linked ot data contained in the DHIS
    database. The <guimenu>Register Overlay</guimenu> panel will allow you to
    add new layers and determine how they will be represented visually on the
    map.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Display name: </guilabel>Represents your overlay in
        the layer tree in the upper right corner.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Map source file: </guilabel>The GeoJSON file
        name.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Fill color: </guilabel>Decides the fill color if the
        layer is a polygon layer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Fill opacity: </guilabel>Select an opacity level
        between 0 (invisible) and 1 (solid).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Stroke color: </guilabel>The stroke color over lines
        and polygon borders.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Stroke width: </guilabel>Select a stroke width between
        0 and 4.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Copying files to the DHIS application</title>
        <para>Currently, your GeoJSON files should be placed in the
      DHIS2_HOME/geojson of your DHIS application to be accessible to the GIS
      module. If the GeoJSON directory does not exist, you will need to create
      it manually and copy your GeoJSON files there.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Using the GIS module</title>
    <section id="gisThematicMap">
      <title>Thematic mapping</title>
      <para>This panel lets you use your registered maps for thematic mapping. All you need to do is selecting your desired indicator-period-map combination in the left side menu.</para>
      <para>Calculation method
    alludes to the  size  of the legend classes. Set to <guimenuitem>Equal intervals</guimenuitem> they will be “highest map value – lowest map value
    / number of classes”. Set to <guimenuitem>Equal group count</guimenuitem> the legend creator will try to distribute the organisation units evenly. Choose <guimenuitem>Fixed bounds </guimenuitem>and
    you may define your own class break values, e.g. “20,40,60” using a comma to
    seperate each of them.</para>
      <para>The map view combo box lists all map views (favorites) saved by the user. The settings that are stored in the map view will be automatically applied to the thematic map panel.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisFavoriteMapView">
      <title>Register favorite map views</title>
      <para>This window will save the current thematic map view in order to
    restore it whenever you want via the <guimenuitem>map view</guimenuitem> combo box in the <guimenu>thematic map</guimenu> panel. By
    adding your views to DHIS 2 Dashboard you may access them there by
    inserting <guimenuitem>map views</guimenuitem> into one of the link
    areas.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisLegendSet">
      <title>Register legend sets</title>
      <para>A legend set may be connected to many indicators, but an indicator may only have one legend set. Thus, you may select many indicators when you create a legend set. When an indicator that has a legend set is selected in the <guimenu>thematic map</guimenu> panel, the number of classes, low color and high color is automatically set.</para><para>Example usage (vaccination coverage): Firstly, create the legends that are going to constitute the legend set. The first one could be &quot;Low bad&quot; (display name), 0 (start value), 30 (end value), red (color). Then create &quot;Medium&quot; / 30 / 70 / yellow and finally &quot;High good&quot; / 70 / 100 / green. Now, open the &quot;legend set&quot; panel, type e.g. &quot;High is good&quot; as display name and select the desired legends below. Multi-select your three legends by pressing and holding the Ctrl/Shift button when selecting. Then click the register button to store the legend set. Assign indicators/data elements to your legend set in one of the two last panels. Select the legend set in the combo box and multi-select items in the list below. Click the assign button to update the legend set.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="gisImageExport">
      <title>Exporting/saving map images</title>
      <para>Click the image icon on the map toolbar and the print window will open. Title: Image title, will appear as a headline in the image. Layers: Choose whether polygons, points or both will be printed. Width/Height: The pixel resolution of the image. Choose among the predefined &quot;small&quot; (800x600), &quot;medium&quot; (1190x880), &quot;large&quot; (1920x1200) or type the exact number of pixels yourself (type the number only, avoid text like &quot;px&quot;). If you want to exclude the legend from the image, untick the legend checkbox. Finally click the export button to print the image (PNG).</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  </chapter>


  <chapter>
    <title>Import and export</title>
    <highlights>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Learning objectives:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para> After reading this module you will be able to understand:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Why do we need functions of export and import data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to export data from DHIS2</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> How to import data into DHIS2</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </highlights>
    <section>
      <title>What is import and export?</title>
      <para>In a primary health system, the HMIS typically involves a distributed application, where the same application is running in different geographical locations (PHCs,CHCs, hospitals, districts, and state). Most of these physical locations do not have Internet connectivity, and hence they work offline. At some point (normally at the district level), the data needs to be synchronised in order to have a consolidated database for the a particular geographical region. For this, it is important to be able to export data from one location (which is working offline, say at the health facility level) to another one say at the district level where the data would need to be imported. This feature of exporting and importing is thus a crucial function of a HMIS. This feature also helps us overcome the dependency on Internet to some degree, as data updates can be transferred via USB key where there is no connectivity, or through email where there is limited Internet connectivity. DHIS 2 provides robust export-import functionality to fulfil these needs. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="export">
      <title>Exporting data</title>
      <para>In the case on on-line data entry, all data is saved into one database only. In an offline deployment, each deployment will have a separate database in their local system. So the data will be stored in their local database. In an offline deployment, after the data entry is finished, it will need to be manually sent to the next level of where the application is running. In an on-line application, however, that is not required, as all data is stored at a central location using the Internet. </para>
      <section>
        <title>Exporting from DHIS2</title>
        <para>The export option can be made use of by selecting it as follows. The import or export is available only when the selected organisation (source/destination) has defined datasets. This is because datasets help to define which data is to be or is being exported. Further, which specific data elements get exported is determined by the composition of the dataset being exported. If there are no datasets defined for an organisation unit, it indicates that no data values are registered for this level of organisation or lower. To access the main Import-Export module, choose <guimenu>Services-&gt;Import-Export</guimenu></para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/import_export/Import_export_main.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>The exported data values are stored in an xml file. The file name is defined by the name of the source organisation unit and the period to allow the receiving organisation unit to identify the source and the period of the export file. The XML is placed in your home directory (On Windows this is normally <filename>C:\Documents and Settings\</filename> under the sub-directories <filename>/dhis / import-export</filename>. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Exporting data to other DHIS2 systems</title>
        <para>Once the data export screen is displayed, select the Organisation unit, period and dataset for which data export should be selected.Finally click on the export option that will be available on the lower left side of displayed screen. If there are no datasets defined for an organisation unit, it indicates that no data values are registered for this level of organisation or lower. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/import_export/export_to_dhis2.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>A pop-up save option will appear on the displayed screen (see picture below) prompting the saving of the exported data. You may save the export folder on your desktop or any other folder by selecting the Save to Disk option from the pop-up prompt. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/import_export/export_file_popup.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Exporting metadata to other DHIS2 systems</title>
        <para/>
        <section>
          <title>Metadata export</title>
          <para>Metadata is &quot;data about data&quot;. In the context of DHIS2, metadata consists of definitions of data elements, indicators, the structure and names contained in the organizational hierarchy, and other options. Click on the &quot;Metadata export&quot; link from the main &quot;Data export&quot; screen in order to access this. Just select the feature that you wish to export and click &quot;Export&quot;. This metadata file can then be transmitted just like a data file, except it will contain information on the definitions of the various features, as opposed to the values of the data themselves. </para>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/import_export/metdata_export.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Detailed metadata export</title>
          <para>The &quot;Detailed metadata&quot; function will allow you to export specific data element and indicator definitions. Just click &quot;Detailed Metadata Export&quot; and select the data elements and indicators that you wish to export. Click &quot;Export&quot; and save the file to a desired location. This file can then be transmitted via email or USB key to other DHIS2 installations. </para>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/import_export/metadata_detail.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>IXF data export</title>
        <para>DHIS2 support export to the Indicator Exchange Format 2 developed by UNAIDS. The IXF data exchange standard has been implemented ,with various levels of compatibility, between several information management systems including CRIS version 2, DevInfo version 5, KIDS developed by FAO, DHIS 1.4, DHIS2, and HealthMapper version 4 developed by WHO. A more detailed discussion on the use of the IXF data exchange format. </para>
        <para>The IXF data export is essentially the same as a standard DHIS 2 DXF export, but results in a file format that is compatible with IXF 2. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>IXF Metadata export</title>
        <para>The IXF detailed metadata export provides the same functionality of the standard DHIS2 detailed metadata export, except that the resulting file is compatible with the IXF data exchange format. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>DHIS 1.4 Metadata export</title>
        <para>The DHIS 1.4 Metadata export functionality provides the same functionality as the standard DHIS2 metadata export, except that the resulting file can be used to transmit metadata information to DHIS 1.4 systems. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>DHIS 1.4 Detailed Metadata Export</title>
        <para>The DHIS 1.4 Metadata export functionality provides the same functionality as the detailed DHIS2 metadata export, except that the resulting file can be used to transmit metadata information to DHIS 1.4 systems. Simply select the data elements and indicators that you want and click &quot;Export&quot; to begin the export process.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>PDF Metadata Export</title>
        <para>Auctor natoque ve vulputate quam. Quam duis posuere risus felis mus class tempor eu sociosqu. Risus duis penatibus turpis, tristique dictum enim est. Quisque mi pulvinar ultrices, fusce diam porttitor mi hendrerit viverra, augue leo vestibulum rutrum. Ridiculus dictumst luctus. Eros.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="import">
      <title>Importing data</title>
      <section>
        <title>DXF Import</title>
        <para>The Data Exchange Format (DXF) is the default XML schema that is used to transport data between two disconnected DHIS2 systems. Importing data from another DHIS2 system is simple. Just select &quot;Services-&gt;Import-Export-Import&quot;. Click the &quot;Browse&quot; button, and select the name of the file that you wish to import as shown below. </para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Default import screen</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="40%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/import_export/import_default.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Importing data </title>
        <para>The import option allows different instance of DHIS2 to receive standardised set of data in the absence of a networked system. Typically, a data set is exported from one DHIS instance (e.g. a district level system) to another system (e.g. a provincial level system). DHIS2 is capable of importing data from other systems that either support the DXF of IXF formats. DHIS2 is capable of importing data directly from a DHIS 1.4 Access database. Each of these options will be discussed in the following sections. </para>
        <para>DHIS2 is also capable of importing data through the Excel reporting module. The reader is referred to the appropriate chapter for detailed information. </para>
        <section>
          <title>Importing data from other DHIS2 systems</title>
          <para>Data can be imported into different instances of DHIS2 through the use of the DXF data exchange format. There are two screens that are used to import data, with default and advanced options. </para>
          <para>The default data import menu can be accessed by clicking the <guimenuitem>&quot;Import&quot;</guimenuitem> from the main <guimenuitem>Import-Export</guimenuitem> screen. By clicking the <guibutton>&quot;Browse&quot;</guibutton> button, you can select a file from you local file system. This file may have been received by email, copied from another users system, or received on a CD for example. Simply select the file that you wish to import. </para>
          <para/>
          <para>There are three separate options for importing data. </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Import: This option will import the contents of the import file directly into the database.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Preview: This option will enable a preview of the contents of the import file. In the preview one can get an overwiev of the data to be imported, discard unwanted elements and match import elements to existing ones.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Analysis: This option will enable an analysis of the contents of the import file. The analysis will search for and examine anomalies in the data, like violations of unique names constraints and invalid indicator formulas. This is useful when importing from external applications where data constraints might be less rigid than in DHIS 2.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE: We highly recommend always using the Preview option</emphasis> when importing data to make sure you keep control over any changes to your metdata and databases being out of synch on data elements or orgunit names.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <section id="importpreview">
            <title>Preview before importing</title>
            <para>Before doing the import into your database it is highly recommended to preview the data to make sure no changes to the metdata (data element and/or orgunit names) have taken place at the source DHIS2 installation. Select Preview in the Type field in the Import window. In the preview window it is<emphasis role="bold"/><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">IMPORTANT</emphasis> to look for New and Updates in metadata.</emphasis> DO NOT just click the Import all button without carefully reviewing the information in the preview window. Importing new data elements or orgunits without checking properly whether they are really new or just old names can cause a corrupted database with duplicate or incomplete data, so be careful! </para>
            <para>Procedure for handling New or Updates in the preview: </para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">If new:</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>If there are new data elements, indicators, or orgunits, first make sure whether they really are new or not. Data elements are rarely new, most of the time they are the old name of something that has been changed in the destination database (e.g. a master db at the national level). If you have changed some data elements names at the national level and these have not yet been updated in the district database, the old names that are in the district export files will appear as new data elements in your import preview. It is very important that you tell the DHIS that these are only just old names of a data element that already exists in your database, if not you will have two data elements meaning the same thing and both with an incomplete set of data. Use the match new to existing button to link the new data elements (that really are old) to the updated names in your national database, and make sure that the source database updates its metdata before the next data export. </para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">If updates: </emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Only the newer updates are shown in the preview. This means the record has been updated more recently in the district/hospital than in the zonal/national database you are importing into. If you are not sure whether you want to import the update or not, you can select the record and click on the compare to existing button to see exactly which changes that have been made in the updated object. </para>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Data Administration</title>
    <para>The data administration module provides a range of functions to ensure that the data stored in the DHIS2 database is integral and that the database performance is optimised. These functions should be executed on a regular basis by a data administrator to ensure that the quality of the data stored is optimal. </para>
    <section id="dataBrowser">
      <title>Data browser</title>
      <para>The data browser maintenance module allows the user to produce a summary of the data contained in the DHIS2 database. This summary provides the number of data element values that have been recorded for a given time interval and then grouped by the following options:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data sets</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data element groups</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Organisational unit groups</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Organisational units</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Each of these options can be accessed by selecting the desired option from <guilabel>&quot;Browse by&quot; </guilabel>drop-down menu. </para>
      <para>In order to produce a summary of submitted data for a given period and grouped by data sets, the user should follow this procedure. Begin by selecting a given periodicity type (e.g. Weekly, monthly, yearly, etc) and then a time interval (e.g. January 2009 to March 2009). Select the type of summary to be produced (e.g. Dataset) from the &quot;Browse by&quot; drop-down menu. Click the &quot;Browse&quot; button to view the summary. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="70%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_browser1.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>A summary of the number of data element values that have been submitted over the user selected time period is shown below. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_browsing_data_sets.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para> By clicking on the name of the individual dataset, a more detailed summary of each data element can be obtained as shown below. A cross-tab table summarising each time period will be shown. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_browser_dataset_detail.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>The functionality of the grouping by Datasets, Data element groups, and Organisational groups is essentially the same. </para>
      <para>The functionality of grouping by organisation units will be discussed below. Begin by selecting &quot;Organisation units&quot; from the &quot;Browse by&quot; drop-down menu. The organisational hierarchy present in the database will now be displayed. Organisational units can be expanded by clicking on the plus symbol in the organisational tree view.</para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_browser_org_unit1.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para> By clicking on an organisational unit, and the clicking the &quot;Browse&quot; button, a summary of submitted data elements present in the database is returned for all immediate children of the selected organisational as shown below</para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_browser_orgunit2a.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>By clicking on one of the organisational units, a detailed list of data elements is presented by each time period as shown below. <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="60%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_browser_orgunit2.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>
      <para>For each of the data browser summaries, a PDF export can be produced by specifying a filename in the &quot;Filename&quot; field, selecting a font size, a page layout (Landscape or Portrait) and pressing the <guibutton>&quot;Export PDF&quot;</guibutton> button. You will then be prompted to select a location to save the file to, which can then be viewed with any PDF reader (e.g. Adobe Acrobat Reader, xpdf, etc). </para>
    </section>
    <section id="dataIntegrity">
      <title>Data integrity</title>
      <para>DHIS2 can perform a wide range of data integrity checks on the data contained in the database. Identifying and correcting data integrity issues is extremely important for ensuring that the data used for analysis purposes is valid. Each of the data integrity checks that are performed by the system will be described, along with general procedures that can be performed to resolve these issues. </para>
      <section>
        <title>Data elements without data set</title>
        <para>Each data element must be assigned to a data set. Values for data elements will not be able to be entered into the system if a data element is not assigned to a data set. Choose Maintenance-&gt;Datasets-&gt;Edit from the main menu and then add the &quot;orphaned&quot; data element to the appropriate data set. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Data elements without groups</title>
        <para>Some Data Elements have been allocated to several Data Element Groups. This is currently not allowed, because it will result in duplication of linked data records in the PivotSource recordsets that `feed` the pivot tables. Go to Maintenance -&gt; Data Element Groups to review each Data Element identified and remove the incorrect Group allocations.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Data elements assigned to data sets with different period types</title>
        <para>Data Elements should not be assigned to two separate data sets whose period types differ. The recommended approach would be to create two separate data elements (for instance a monthly and yearly data element) and assign these to respective datasets. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Data sets not assigned to organisation units</title>
        <para>All data sets should be assigned to at least one organisation unit. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Indicators with identical formulas</title>
        <para>Although this rule will not affect data quality, it generally does not make sense to have two indicators with the exact same definition. Review the identified indicators and their formulas and delete or modify any indicator that appears to be the duplicate.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Indicators without groups</title>
        <para>All Data Elements and Indicators must be assigned to at least one group, so these Indicators need to be allocated to their correct Data Element and Indicator Group. Go to Maintenance -&gt; Indicator Groups, and allocate each of the `Orphaned` Indicators to its correct group.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Invalid indicator numerators</title>
        <para>Violations of this rule may be caused by an incorrect reference to a deleted or modified data element. Review the indicator and make corrections to the numerator definition. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Invalid indicator denominators</title>
        <para>Violations of this rule may be caused by an incorrect reference to a deleted or modified data element. Review the indicator and make corrections to the denominator definition. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title> Organisation units with cyclic references</title>
        <para>Organisation units cannot be both parent and children of each other, directly nor indirectly.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Orphaned organisation units</title>
        <para>All organisation units must exist within the organisation unit hierarchy. Go to Organisation-&gt;Hierarchy Operations and move the offending organisation unit into the proper position in the hierarchy. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Organisation units without groups</title>
        <para>All organisation units <emphasis>must</emphasis> be allocated to at least <emphasis>one</emphasis> group. The problem might either be that you have not defined any `compulsory` OrgUnit Group Set at all, or that there are violations of the `compulsory` rule for some OrgUnits . NOTE: If you have defined no `compulsory` OrgUnit Group Sets, then you must first define them by going to Maintenance -&gt; Organisation units-&gt;Organisation unit group sets and define at least one `compulsory` Group Set (the group set `OrgUnitType` are nearly universally relevant). If you have the relevant group sets, go to Maintenance -&gt; OrgUnit Groups to review each OrgUnit identified and add the relevant Group allocation.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Organisation units violating compulsory group sets</title>
        <para>These organisation units have not been assigned to the any organisation unit group within one of the <emphasis>compulsory</emphasis> organisation unit group sets. When a group set is defined as `compulsory`, it means that an organisation unit must be allocated to at least one organisation unit group within that group set. For instance, all organisation units must belong to one of the groups in the `organisation unitType` group set. It might belong to the `Hospital` or the `Clinic` or any other `type` group - but it must belong to exactly one of them. Go to Maintenance -&gt; organisation unit-&gt;Organisation unit groups to review each organisation unit identified in the integrity check. Allocate all organisation units to exactly one group. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Organisation units violating exclusive group sets</title>
        <para>Some organisation units have been allocated to several organisation unit groups that are members of the same exclusive organisation unit group set. When a group set is defined as exclusive, it means that an organisation unit can <emphasis>only</emphasis> be allocated to <emphasis>one</emphasis> organisation unit group within that Group Set. For instance, one organisation unit cannot normally belong to the both the &apos;Hospital&apos; and &apos;Clinic&apos; groups , but rather to only to one of them. Go to Maintenance -&gt; organisation unit-&gt;Organisation unit groups to review each organisation unit identified in the integrity check. Remove the organisation unit from all groups except the one that it should be allocated to. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title> Organisation unit groups without group sets</title>
        <para>The organisation unit groups listed here have not been allocated to a group set. Go to Maintenance-&gt;Organisation unit-&gt;Organisation unit group sets and allocate the Organisation unit group to the appropriate group set. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Validation rules without groups</title>
        <para>All validation rules must be assigned to a group. Go to <command>Services-&gt;Data quality-&gt;Validation rule group</command> and assign the offending validation rule to a group. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Invalid validation rule left side expressions</title>
        <para>An error exists in the left-side validation rule definition. Go to <command>Services-&gt;Data quality-&gt;Validation rule</command> and click the &quot;Edit&quot; icon on the offending rule. Press &quot;Edit left side&quot; and make the corrections that are required. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Invalid validation rule right side expressions</title>
        <para>An error exists in the left-side validation rule definition. Go to <command>Services-&gt;Data quality-&gt;Validation rule</command> and click the &quot;Edit&quot; icon on the offending rule. Press &quot;Edit right side&quot; and make the corrections that are required.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="dataArchive">
      <title>Data Archive</title>
      <para>The purpose of the data archive function is to move data which is currently not being used for analysis to a secondary storage location in order to improve performance of the application. Data can be both archived and unarchived. When archiving data one moves it from the primary storage to the secondary storage location, while unarchiving moves it from the secondary storage location to the primary. Analysis functionality in DHIS 2 heavily utilizes queries to the data value database table, and by reducing the size of this table these operations will be significantly faster. Typically one would want to archive data that is older than two years.</para>
      <para>To archive data, first enter a start date and an end date for the time span of the data which should be archived. Then press the archive button. The operation might take a few minutes.</para>
      <para>To unarchive data, first enter a start date and an end date for the time span of the data which should be unarchived. Then press the unarchive button. The operation might take a few minutes.</para>
      <para>In some cases you might end up with overlapping data. For instance one might archive data for a given timespan, then later enter data for a period in that timespan. In such cases the system will automatically overwrite the oldest of the overlapping values with the newest during the archive or unarchive operation.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="patientDataArchive">
      <title>Beneficiary Data Archive</title>
      <para>The purpose of the beneficiary data archive function is to move beneficiary data value which is currently not being used for analysis to a secondary storage location in order to improve performance of the application. Data can be both archived and unarchived. When archiving data one moves it from the primary storage to the secondary storage location, while unarchiving moves it from the secondary storage location to the primary. Analysis functionality in DHIS 2 heavily utilizes queries to the data value database table, and by reducing the size of this table these operations will be significantly faster. Typically one would want to archive beneficiary data that is older than two years.</para>
      <para>To archive beneficiary data, first enter a start date and an end date for the time span of the data which should be archived. Then press the archive button. The operation might take a few minutes.</para>
      <para>To unarchive beneficiary data, first enter a start date and an end date for the time span of the data which should be unarchived. Then press the unarchive button. The operation might take a few minutes.</para>
      <para>In some cases you might end up with overlapping data. For instance one might archive beneficiary data for a given timespan, then later enter data for a period in that timespan. In such cases the system will automatically overwrite the oldest of the overlapping values with the newest during the archive or unarchive operation.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="maintenance">
      <title>Maintenance</title>
      <para>The data maintenance module has five options, each described below. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Clear data mart (aggregated datavalues)</para>
          <para>The data mart is where DHIS 2 stores aggregated data produced during the export to data mart process. This function clears the database table which contains aggregated data element values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Clear data mart (aggregated indicatorvalues)</para>
          <para>The data mart is where DHIS 2 stores aggregated data produced during the export to data mart process. This function clears the database table which contains aggregated indicator values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Clear zero values</para>
          <para>This function removes zero data values from the database. Values registered for data elements with aggregation operator <emphasis role="italic">average</emphasis> is not removed, as such values will be significant when aggregating the data, contrary to values registered for data elements with aggregation operator <emphasis role="italic">sum</emphasis>. Reducing the number of data values will improve system performance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Clear dataset completeness</para>
          <para>This function removes aggregated dataset completeness values. This data is produced and used by report tables.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prune periods</para>
          <para>This function removes all periods which have no registered data values. Reducing the number of periods will improve system performance.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="resourceTables">
      <title>Resource tables</title>
      <para>Resource tables are supporting tables that are used during analysis of data. One would typically join the contents of these tables with the data value table when doing queries from third-party applications like Microsoft Excel. Simply select the tables that should be regenerated and press &quot;Generate tables&quot;. Regeneration of the resource tables should only be done once all data integrity issues are resolved. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Organisation unit structure (orgunitstructure)</para>
          <para>This table should be regenerated any time there have been any changes made to the organisational unit hierarchy. This table provides information about the organisation unit hierarchy. It has one row for each organisation unit, one column for each organisation unit level and the organisation unit identifiers for all parents in the lineage as values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Exclusive organisation unit groupset structure normalized (orgunitgroupsetstructure)</para>
          <para>This table provides information about the which organisation units are member of which organisation unit group sets.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data element group set structure (_dataelementgroupsetstructure)</para>
          <para>This table provides information about which data elements are members of which data element group sets. The table has one row for each data element, one column for each data element group set and the names of the data element group as values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Indicator group set structure (_indicatorgroupsetstructure)</para>
          <para>This table provides information about which indicators are members of which indicator group sets. The table has one row for each indicator, one column for each indicator group set and the names of the indicator group as values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Organisation unit group set structure (_organisationunitgroupsetstructure)</para>
          <para>This table provides information about which organisation units are members of which organisation unit group sets. The table has one row for each organisation unit, one column for each organisation unit group set and the names of the organisation unit groups as values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Category structure (_categorystructure)</para>
          <para>This table provides information about which data elements are members of which categories. The table has one row for each data element, one column for each category and the names of the category options as values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data element category option combo name (categoryoptioncomboname)</para>
          <para>This table should be regenerated any time there have been changes made to the category combination names. It contains readable names for the various combinations of categories.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="organisationUnitMerge">
      <title>Organisation unit merge</title>
      <para>This function is useful when two organisation units need to be merged, eg. it is decided that one facility will be shut down and its services will be provided by a nearby facility.</para>
      <para>Start by selecting the organisation unit to eliminate from the tree and click <emphasis role="italic">confirm</emphasis>. Then select the organisation unit to keep and click <emphasis role="italic">confirm</emphasis> again. Finally, verify the selection and click <emphasis role="italic">merge</emphasis>. </para>
      <para>In the sitation where data exist for the organisation unit to eliminate and not for the one to keep, the data will be moved to the one to keep. When data exists for both organisation units, the data will be summarized and moved to the one to keep. When data exists only for the one to keep, no action is taken. The organisation unit to eliminate will eventually be deleted.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="duplicateDataElimination">
      <title>Duplicate data elimination</title>
      <para>This function is useful when data has been entered mistakenly for two data elements which represents the same phenomena.</para>
      <para>Start by selecting the data element to eliminate from the list and click confirm. Then select the data element to keep and click confirm again. Finally, verify the selection and click merge.</para>
      <para>In the situation where data exists for the data element to eliminate and not for the one to keep, the data will be moved to the one to keep. When data exists for both data elements, the data which was updated last will be used. When data exists only for the one to keep, no action will be taken. The data element to eliminate will eventually be deleted, except when it is a multidimensional data element and has other data registered.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="dataStatistics">
      <title>Data statistics</title>
      <para>The data statistics module provides an overview of the number of objects stored in the DHIS2 database. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_stats.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>The total number of each type of object is presented in a table, as well as a graph. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="dataLocking">
      <title>Data locking</title>
      <para>This module gives users the privilege of locking certain datasets for chosen organisation units. This encourages timely data entry and prevents unwanted to changes to the data once it has been entered. When the Data Administration option is chosen the data locking interface is displayed. The user has to select the periodicity of the report e.g. monthly, quarterly or yearly for which the data is to be locked. The month, quarter or year for which the reports are to be locked is then specified. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_locking_select1.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>The unlocked data sets for the period are displayed and the user will then have to choose the data sets to be locked. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_locking_select2.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>After choosing the datasets to be locked, double click on each one by one to display the organisation unit tree in the field below. Click on the organisation unit to lock the dataset. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/data_locking_select3.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>The <guibutton>Apply Locks on All</guibutton> button locks the dataset for all the organisation units to which that dataset has been assigned. <guibutton>Remove locks on All</guibutton> removes all locks put on the organisation units corresponding to the selected dataset. After the operations are completed the user must click <guibutton>Save</guibutton> to apply the settings. The <guibutton>Lock at level</guibutton> button locks datasets at a particular level that the user chooses. . <guibutton>Unlock at Level</guibutton> removes locks that have been put on the organisation units corresponding to the selected dataset at the selected level. After the operations are completed, the user must click <guibutton>Save</guibutton> to apply the settings. The <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button will also lock those organisation unit datasets that have been specified by the user. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="zeroValueStorage">
      <title>Zero value storage</title>
      <para>The zero value storage function makes it possible to define for which data elements the system should store zero values. In most cases zeros are significant only for a subset of the data elements in the database. Zero values will be ignored during data entry for selected data elements.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="cacheStatistics">
      <title>Cache Statistics </title>
      <para>This option is for system administrators only to use. The cache statistics shows the status of the application level cache. The application level cache refers to the objects and query results that the application is caching in order to speed up performance. If the database has been modified directly the application cache needs to be cleared for it to take effect.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Beneficiaries and Programs</title>
    <para>In this section you will learn how to:</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Register beneficiaries and enrol into a program</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create beneficiary attributes and attribute groups</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Create a beneficiary identifier type</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Create a relationship type</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Create program and attribute</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Define a beneficiary aggregation</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Define a validation criteria</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Beneficiary Mobile Setting</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <section id="patient">
		<title>Beneficiary</title>
        <para>Beneficiary section provides a mechanism for administrating a beneficiary, and it includes registering a new beneficiary, setting relationships for beneficiaries and enrolling a beneficiary into a program.</para>
        <para>To access the beneficiary maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary.</para>
		<para>For the registration (creating) process, the details - which are related to the personal information, identification, contact and location details, and health provider details, are entered.</para>
		<para>Beneficiary is provided with an unique identification number. This ID number doesl not match with the identification number of any other persons in the state jurisdiction. The issue of identification number will be the responsibility of facilities where the beneficiary is registered in first time.</para>
		<para>To show the beneficiary list, select a facility on the left (the organization unit tree) and then click the "List All Beneficiaries" button.</para>
		<para>To search for beneficiaries by name, identifier or beneficiary attributes, enter a key word into the text field and then click the "Search" button (or even just press Enter key).</para>
		<para>To add a new beneficiary, click the "Add new" button.</para>
		<para>To update information for a beneficiary, click the "Edit Profile" icon, the third icon under Operations, corresponding to the beneficiary you would like to modify.</para>
		<para>After beneficiary registration, the new-created beneficiary needs to be enrolled in at least one of the programs available by specifying a date of enrollment and a date of incident. A date of enrollment is the date of registration of the beneficiary with a facility. A date of incidence is the date when the beneficiary got the disease or he/she has just been committed to an equivalent program for being followed-up.</para>
		<para>For instance, when a person comes for a treatment, i.e. pregnant woman. Then the system should automatically generate visit dates for the subsequent ANC visits. But to generate these visit schedules, we need to ask the mother when was the date she got pregnant. The day she came for a treatment at a facility/clinic might not be much necessary but the day she figured out her pregnancy by her self or by a nurse/mid-wife, therefore for a better treatment ( by having appropriate visit dates ), we need to know the information about the last date she got menstruation  - that is what the Date of Incidence all about.</para>
		<para>To open the relationship list of a beneficiary, click the "Relationship Management" icon which is the fourth icon under Operations.</para>
		<para>To registry new a person who has a relationship with the beneficiary, click the "Add dependent" icon.</para>
		<para>To show details of a beneficiary, click the "Show details" icon.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="patient_attribute">
		<title>Beneficiary attribute</title>
        <para>Beneficiary attribute section provides a mechanism for defining a beneficiary attribute. The defined attributes will be used for registering a beneficiary.</para>
        <para>To access the beneficiary attribute maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary Attribute.</para>
		<para>To define a new beneficiary attribute, click the "Add new" button. Fill all fields with red asterisk, and click "Add" button.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="patient_attribute_group">
		<title>Beneficiary attribute group</title>
        <para>Beneficiary attribute group section provides a mechanism for classifying beneficiary attributes. For instance, two attributes "Register person Phone number" and "Register person Address" might be grouped together into a beneficiary attribute group "Details of Registered person".</para>
        <para>To access the beneficiary attribute group maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary Attribute Group.</para>
		<para>To define a new attribute group, click the "Add new" button. Fill in the "Name" and "Description" fields and then select attributes that should belong to the group from the left panel. Click the "Move selected items" button to add the selected attributes to the attribute group. Click the "Remove selected items" button to remove attributes from the group that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the "Add" button to save changes, or the "Cancel" button to discard any changes.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="patient_identifier_type">
		<title>Beneficiary identifier type</title>
        <para>Beneficiary identifier type section provides a mechanism for defining identifiers associated with the registration of a beneficiary, such as Passport number, PAN, driving license, driving license, health identifier and so on.</para>
		<para>To access the beneficiary identifier type maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary Identifier Type.</para>
		<para>To define a new identifier type, click the "Add new" button. Fill all fields with red asterisk, and click "Add" button.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="relationship_type">
		<title>Relationship type</title>
        <para>Relationship type section provides a mechanism for defining any relationship types and link beneficiaries through these relationship types by creating specific relationships.</para> 
		<para>To access the relationship type maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Relationship Type.</para>
		<para>To define a new relationship type, click the "Add new" button. Fill all fields in "Add new Relationship Type" form, and click "Add" button.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="patient_organisation_unit_registration">
		<title>Beneficiary Organisation Unit Registration</title>
        <para>Beneficiary organisation unit registration section provides a mechanism for managing facilities which allow to registry new beneficiaries  or not.</para> 
		<para>To access the beneficiary registration maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary Registration.</para>
		<para>There are two processes for registering facilities. The first one is where the administrator will say that beneficiaries can register here. The second is where provides services ( Child Health program, Mother Care program, ...) for registered beneficiaries.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="program">
		<title>Program</title>
        <para>Program section provides a mechanism for defining a health program. All name based case entry is organised through the use of programs.</para>
		<para>To access the program maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Program.</para>
		<para>A health program includes some specific stages because of having multiple encounters for a given program. E.g. once a pregnant woman enrolls to the "ANC Program", she will get examination and treatments for the first trimester, the second trimester and/or the third trimester. These encounters in most cases are mandatory, and there will be dropouts in some cases, in which a pregnant woman should go through after she enrolled in the "ANC Program". So the specific stages of the health program are defined when a health program is created/specified.</para> 
		<para>To define a new program, click the "Add new" button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and then click the "Add" button.</para>
		<para>You can assign the facilities to a program in the Program Management ( in which a list of available programs are shown) by clicking on the blue folder icon, which is the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the program you would like to modify.</para>
		<para>The function "Define Program Validation" is designed for defining validations of a program in which you would like to modify after entering patient data values for program stages. </para>
		<para>For instance, Parity, Previous live birth male, Previous live birth female, Previous still birth are patient data elements. They belong to many stages. And if data value of Parity is 0, then ( Previous live birth female + Previous still birth ) = 0. Besides, if a patient data element exists into many program stages, the system will check whether the values of the patient data element are in all program stages of the program or not.</para>
		<para>For instance, TT1 is a patient data element. It exists into program stages as follows Checkup 1, Checkup 2, Checkup 3. If the data value of this data element into Checkup 1 is null, the data values into Checkup 2, Checkup 3 should be null.</para>
		<para>To open Program stage management form, click the "Program Stage Management" icon.</para>
		<para>To define a new program stage, into "Program Stage Management" form, click the "Add new" button. Fill in the "Name" and "Description" fields and then select the data elements that should belong to the group from the left panel. Click the "Move selected" button to add the selected data elements to the right panel. Click the "Remove selected" button to remove data elements that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the "Add" button to save changes, or the "Cancel" button to discard any changes.</para>
		<para>Your program will then be ready to be used to enroll beneficiaries (which are modified/created under Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiaries) and enter data under the data-entry function Services->Name Based Data Records->Data Entry or Multiple Data.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="program_attribute">
		<title>Program attribute</title>
        <para>Program attribute section provides a mechanism for defining a program attribute. The defined program attributes will be used when a beneficiary unenroll from a program. You can create/edit program attributes in Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Progam Attribute.</para> 
		<para>To access the program attribute maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Program Attribute.</para>
		<para>To create a new program, click the "Add new" button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and click "Add" button.</para>
		<para>NOTE: There are two program attributes are created for all programs as default to track up program un-enrollment when a beneficiary is announced to un-enrol the program or to be dead. And these two attributes are: Dead (with Yes/No value type) and Closed Date (with Date value type). Moreover, when a beneficiary un-enrolls from a program, the un-enrolled date is required.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="beneficiary_aggregation_query_builder">
		<title>Beneficiary aggregation query builder</title>
        <para>Beneficiary aggregation query builder section is the core functionality for linking data between name-based information tracking system – NBITS ( beneficiaries, programs, etc ) and aggregate management system ( dataset, report, charts, etc.) by defining the linking/aggregating rules.</para> 
        <para>This provides two functions. The first is the "Beneficiaries Aggregation Query Builder", a tool to define a formula, an expression, a rule for aggregation data from the tracking (name-based) system to the aggregation system. The second is the  "Beneficiary Aggregation" used for generating routine data values from patient data value by periods ( or other interval if desired ) and by a facility.</para>
        <para>To access "Beneficiaries Aggregation Query Builder" module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder.</para>
        <para>To create a new beneficiaries aggregation query builder, click the "Add new" button. Fill in "Description" field and select an aggregation "Data Element" from a data element group.</para>
        <para>Then select a program and a corresponding program stage, double click the patient data element you need to create a condition, the equivalent code of it will be showed in the condition box. In addition, you can click the operator buttons to create operators for a condition.</para>
        <para>To access "Beneficiary Aggregation" module, choose Services->Name Based Data Records->Beneficiary Aggregation.</para>
        <para>For instance, find the number of the children vaccinated BCG by defining a linking rule between the data elements of aggregate dataset named "Number of children - BCG" and the data element of a program stage named "BCG dose given date".</para>
        <para>1. Choose Maintenance->Data Element and Indicators->Data Element, define two new data elements. One is "Number of children - BCG" with "Aggregate" Domain Type. Two is "BCG dose give date" with "Patient" Domain Type.</para>
        <para>2. Choose Maintenance->Data Element and Indicators->Data Element Group, create a new data element group named "BCG DataElement Group" and add "Number of children - BCG" data element into the group.</para>
        <para>3. Choose Maintenance->Datasets->Dataset, create a new dataset named "BCG Report" and add "Number of children - BCG" data element into the dataset.</para>
        <para>4. Choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Program, create a program named "Child Health Program" with a stage named "Birth Details" and add the "BCG dose give date" data element into this stage. Then assign it to "Ho Chi Minh city" facility.</para>
        <para>5. Choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Program->Beneficiary, select "Ho Chi Minh city" and create three beneficiaries named "Micheal", "Alice" and "Tom" and enroll them into "Child Health Program".</para>
        <para>6. Create a new beneficiary aggregation query builder named "Number of children - BCG Builder" to linking between the data elements.</para>
        <para>6.1. Choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder, click the "Add new" button.</para>
        <para>6.2. Fill in "The number of children - BCG Builder" for the description field.</para>
        <para>6.3. In the Data Element Group combobox, select "BCG DataElement Group".</para>
        <para>6.4. In the Data Element combobox, select "Number of children - BCG (default)"</para>
        <para>6.5. In the Program combobox, select "Child Health Program".</para>
        <para>6.6. In the Program Stage combobox, select "Birth Details".</para>
        <para>6.7. In the Data Element list box, double click the "BCG dose give date". And click the "Is not null" button</para>
        <para>6.8. Click the "is not null" operator button.</para>
        <para>6.9. Click "Add" button.</para>
        <para>7. Choose Services->Name-Based Data Records->Data Entry, click the "List All Beneficiaries" button.</para>
        <para>7.1. Select beneficiary with name "Micheal" and open the "Birth Details" stage of "Child Health Program". Enter value "2011-02-18" for "BCG dose give date" data element.</para>
        <para>7.2. Select beneficiary with name "Alice" and open the "Birth Details" stage of "Child Health Program". Enter value "2011-02-18" for "BCG dose give date" data element.</para>
        <para>7.3. Select beneficiary with name "Tom" and open the "Birth Details" stage of "Child Health Program". No enter value for "Birth Details" stage.</para>
        <para>Before entering patient data value of the beneficiaries for the stage, choose "Report Date" as "2011-02-28".</para>
        <para>8. Choose Services->Name-Based Data Records->Case Aggregation</para>
        <para>8.1. In Dataset list combo box, select "BCG Report".</para>
        <para>8.2. In From combo box, select "January 2011".</para>
        <para>8.2. In To combo box, select "February 2011".</para>
        <para>8.3. In Organisation Unit Tree Section box, select "Ho Chi Minh city".</para>
        <para>8.4. Click the "Aggregate" button. The result will be shown after running successfully.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="validation_criteria">
		<title>Validation criteria</title>
        <para>Validation criteria section provide a mechanism for defining criteria for beneficiaries when enrolling a program.</para>
        <para>To access the validation criteria maintenance module, choose Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Validation Criteria.</para>
		<para>To create a new validation criterion, click the "Add new" button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and click "Add" button.</para>
		<para>You can assign facilities to a validation criterion in the Validation Criteria Management ( list of available validation criteria are shown ) by clicking on the blue folder icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the validation criterion you would like to assign. Click the "Move selected" button to add the selected programs to the validation criterion. Click the "Remove selected" button to remove programs from the group that have been selected in the right panel. Finally, click the "Save" button to save changes, or the "Cancel" button to discard any changes.</para>
	</section>
   </chapter>
   <chapter>
    <title>Name-Based Data Records</title>
    <para>In this section you will learn how to:</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Input data for treatment stages of a beneficiary</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Summary beneficiary list enrol a certain program by the time</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Create visit plans of beneficiaries by an organisation unit</para>
        </listitem>
		<listitem>
          <para>Calculate and aggregate data of treatment case</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <section id="name_based_data_entry">
		<title>Name-based data entry</title>
        <para>Name-based data entry section provides a mechanism for inputting data in treatment stages for each beneficiary.</para>
		<para>To access the beneficiary data entry module, choose Services->Name-Based Data Records->Data Entry.</para>
		<para>To enter data, you will first have to select a facility for which beneficiaries belong to in order to enter data. Simply clicking the concerned facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen.</para>
		<para>To open data entry form for a beneficiary, please do the steps as follows:</para>
		<para>1. Search beneficiaries: click the List All Beneficiaries button to show all beneficiaries by the selected facility; or select an attribute on the attribute box and enter a key to search beneficiaries. The result list is shown below.</para>
		<para>2. To open treatment form, click the Data Entry icon, the first icon under Operations, corresponding to the beneficiary you would like to input data.</para>
		<para>3. Choose a program which you want input data for the selected beneficiary in the Program list.</para>
		<para>4. Choose a program stage in Program Stage list.</para>
		<para>5. Enter a report data for this stage. The form is shown below.</para>
		<para>You will now enter data for the data entry form. The disabled data fields in data entry form are corresponding to these data elements belong to other stages.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="multi_name_based_data_entry">
		<title>Multiple name-based data entry</title>
        <para>Multiple name-based data entry section provides a mechanism for inputting data for treatment stages of beneficiaries. The benefits of this advanced function is to optimize the time-transition consuming when entering data for a long list beneficiaries by not switching the main window/interface.</para>
		<para>To access the multiple beneficiary data entry module, choose Services->Name-Based Data Records->Multiple Data Entry.</para>
		<para>To enter data, you will first have to select the facility for which beneficiaries belong to in order to enter data. Simply clicking the concerned facility from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen.</para>
		<para>To open data entry form for a beneficiary with Multiple Data Entry function, please do the steps as follows:</para>
		<para>1. Select a program in Program list. The beneficiary list by the selected facility and program is shown. Each beneficiary in the list is shown with each corresponded stages.</para>
		<para>2. To open treatment form, click the date of a program stage corresponding to the beneficiary you would like to input data. A form is shown.</para>
		<para>3. Enter a report data in the form. The data entry form is shown.</para>
		<para>You will now enter data for the data entry form. The disabled data fields in data entry form are corresponding to these data elements belong to other stages.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="program_summary_report">
		<title>Program summary report</title>
        <para>Program summary report section provides a mechanism for getting an overview of the services provided for a program.</para>
		<para>To access the report Management module, choose Services->Name-Based Data Records->Summary Report.</para>
		<para>The first, you have to select the facility where you want to report. Simply clicking on the concerned organisation unit from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen.</para>
		<para>The second, select a program to report. Then enter a start date and an end date for which cases with report data should be included. The date picker widget may be used to select dates.</para>
		<para>Finally, click the Generate button.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="patient_visit_plan">
		<title>Visit plans</title>
        <para>Visit plans section provides feedbacks report to the facilities to help them in planning activities. This is also called as activity plan or visit plan. Basically, view the visit plan to get an overview of outstanding, pending, and completed visits.</para>
		<para>To access the report Management module, choose Services->Name-Based Data Records->Visit Plans.</para>
		<para>The first, you have to select the facility where you want to report. Simply clicking on the concerned organisation unit from the facilities hierarchy displayed on the left side of the data entry screen.</para>
		<para>Then select an attribute in the Sort By box. The visit plan list is shown.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="run_case_aggregation">
		<title>Beneficiary aggregation</title>
        <para>Beneficiary aggregation section provides a mechanism for calculating and aggregating data of treatment case by using beneficiary aggregation query builder defined in Maintenance->Beneficiaries and Programs->Beneficiary Aggregation Query Builder.</para>
		<para>To access the report Management module, choose Services->Name-Based Data Records->Beneficiary Aggregation.</para>
		<para>The first, you have to select a data set in the Dataset List box. A period list which is correspoding to period type of the data set is filled in Form box and To box. The second, select a from-period and a to-period for periods which you want to aggregate data of beneficiaries. The third, select an option in the OrganisationUnit By box. The fourth, select a facility. Finally, click the Aggregate button.</para>
	</section>
   </chapter>
</book>
